<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>R on Phil in the Blank</title><link>/categories/r/</link><description>Recent content in R on Phil in the Blank</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 28 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/categories/r/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Exploring Mental Health Networks</title><link>/projects/pocs-mh-nets/</link><pubDate>Tue, 28 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/projects/pocs-mh-nets/</guid><description>&lt;p>This is a brief project where I look at mental health symptom networks in a large sample of youth from the &lt;a href="https://abcdstudy.org/">ABCD Study&lt;/a> for the course &lt;a href="https://pdodds.w3.uvm.edu/teaching/courses/2021-2022principles-of-complex-systems/">Principles of Complex Systems&lt;/a>. I was largely inspired by the work being done by &lt;a href="https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/full/10.1002/wps.20375">Denny Borsboom&lt;/a> and &lt;a href="http://psychosystems.org/NetworkSchool">company&lt;/a> using network analysis to study mental health. There is still a lot of work to do, but the report for the class can be found &lt;a href="https://github.com/nguyenhphilip/pocs-mh-nets/blob/main/CSYS_Mental_Health_Networks.pdf">here&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Check out &lt;a href="https://psyarxiv.com/f68ej/">this awesome paper&lt;/a> for more on applying complex systems thinking to psychopathology!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="/images/projects/mh-net1.png" alt="">&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Bayesian PCA</title><link>/projects/bayesian-pca/</link><pubDate>Mon, 27 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/projects/bayesian-pca/</guid><description>&lt;p>This is a project I worked on for my Bayesian Statistics course. My partner and I explored Bayesian Principal Component Analysis (BPCA) as an extension of PCA and PPCA on MNIST and an ecological dataset. I learned quite a bit about PCA in the process! The final report can be found &lt;a href="https://github.com/nguyenhphilip/stat330project/blob/main/STAT_330_Preprint_draft.pdf">here&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="/images/projects/bpca1.png" alt="">&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="/images/projects/bpca2.png" alt="">&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Character Space &amp; TV Tropes</title><link>/projects/character-space/</link><pubDate>Wed, 05 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/projects/character-space/</guid><description>&lt;p>This is an exploratory project I worked on with another graduate student in Data Science II. We explore the space of personality in fictional characters using data from &lt;a href="https://openpsychometrics.org/tests/characters/">OpenPsychometrics&lt;/a>. The bulk of the project was spent on probing and describing the space using dimensionality reduction with SVD. A link to the full work is &lt;a href="CSYS_387_Final_Paper.pdf">here&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="/images/projects/cspace1.png" alt="">&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="/images/projects/cspace2.png" alt="">&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Life After: A #NET-COVID Survey of Beliefs</title><link>/projects/life-after/</link><pubDate>Mon, 27 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/projects/life-after/</guid><description>&lt;p>The &lt;a href="https://sites.google.com/view/life-after-covid19/english">Life After&lt;/a> project is a survey of beliefs about what people believe the world will look like after the COVID-19 pandemic ends. I created &lt;a href="https://phil-nguyen.shinyapps.io/life-after/">an interactive website&lt;/a> to show the results of our analyses using R and Shiny.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The motivation:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>COVID-19 is one of the largest pandemics of the century. It will have lasting effects on society around the globe. There has been a great deal of speculation about what those effects may be. But, there has yet to be an assessment of what individuals believe the effects will be. This study aims to create a picture of the world after the pandemic, from the perspectives of individuals across the globe. The survey collects anonymous information about socio-demographic and individual characteristics, and asks questions regarding your beliefs about the future behaviors of yourself and others.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>This project was created as part of the &lt;a href="http://www.combine.umd.edu/network-epidemiology/">Network Epidemiology workshop&lt;/a> presented by the University of Maryland COMBINE program in collaboration with the University of Vermont Complex Systems Center. We had two weeks to design the study, collect responses, and analyze the data.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>All in all, it was a fun project and I learned a lot about Shiny app development, making GIFs, and survey research in general. I am most grateful for the friendships I have developed out of this. Thanks Sam, José, and Rory!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="/images/projects/life-after.png" alt="">&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Prematurity, Mental Health, and Cognition</title><link>/projects/prematurity-analysis/</link><pubDate>Wed, 31 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/projects/prematurity-analysis/</guid><description>&lt;p>This is a project examining the effect of premature birth on mental health and neurocognition in a large sample of youth from the &lt;a href="abcdstudy.org">ABCD Study&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Below is an interactive HTML page using R Markdown for the analyses and visualization. The source code is posted &lt;a href="https://github.com/nguyenhphilip/interactive_analysis_prem">here&lt;/a> and there is an interactive Rmarkdown page &lt;a href="premat">here&lt;/a> as well.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="/images/projects/premat-bruno-img.png" alt="">&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Intro to R Workshop</title><link>/projects/intro-r-workshop/</link><pubDate>Wed, 10 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/projects/intro-r-workshop/</guid><description>&lt;p>These are some slides for an introductory R and Tidyverse workshop I lead for undergraduates and graduate students working in our lab. We ran 4 workshops total:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Day 1: Setup R, RStudio, motivations for learning R&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/1Oeq8iYvr7tOzi3zReJiNiss9iT3ndA3bv2DEhGEwZcQ/edit?usp=sharing">Workshop Day 2&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/12xRbyYcthcle-Td6uL9qzzjI5WkWSfozh7iaXQNFmoE/edit?usp=sharing">Workshop Day 3&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/12LMslY_fMwQ6A5h3vJ2SnOmPThfJwuNvANsT0F3EtMs/edit?usp=sharing">Workshop Day 4&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul></description></item><item><title>Cognition and BOLD Signal Related to Early Stages of Puberty</title><link>/projects/ncog-pub-rome/</link><pubDate>Tue, 25 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/projects/ncog-pub-rome/</guid><description>&lt;p>This is the project I presented at the OHBM 2019 conference in Rome - &lt;a href="https://www.slideshare.net/slideshow/embed_code/key/uJK54jXcatbLwL">&amp;ldquo;Differences in Cognition and BOLD Signal Related to Early Stages of Puberty&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="/images/projects/ohbm_poster_2019.jpg" alt="">&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>ABCD Data Dictionary</title><link>/projects/abcd-dd/</link><pubDate>Wed, 05 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/projects/abcd-dd/</guid><description>&lt;p>I built a searchable data dictionary and ABCD release notes all in one place, which addresses some of the navigational issues I had with NDA&amp;rsquo;s data dictionary.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Unfortunately I can&amp;rsquo;t show the app&amp;rsquo;s source code due to confidentiality, but this is a GIF demonstrating what it does.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="/images/projects/data-dict.gif" alt="">&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Built using R and Shiny. Data pulled from &lt;a href="https://nda.nih.gov/">NDA website&lt;/a>.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>ABCD Database Builder</title><link>/projects/abcd-db-builder/</link><pubDate>Sat, 05 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/projects/abcd-db-builder/</guid><description>&lt;p>This is an app I built in Shiny to help ABCD Researchers download ABCD datasets (Unfortunately I can&amp;rsquo;t show the app due to confidentiality, but the source code is &lt;a href="https://github.com/nguyenhphilip/ABCD_Database_Builder">here.&lt;/a>)&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Here is a GIF demonstrating some of the app&amp;rsquo;s functionality.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>You can select which spreadsheet(s) you want to download, specific variables from the spreadsheets, which visits to include, and what to name your file.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="/images/projects/abcd-db-build.gif" alt="">&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Developed with R and Shiny.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>