<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Life on Phil in the Blank</title>
    <link>//localhost:1313/categories/life/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Life on Phil in the Blank</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 10 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
      <atom:link href="//localhost:1313/categories/life/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Lessons from RRR</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/poems/04-10-23-rrr/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>//localhost:1313/poems/04-10-23-rrr/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Sometimes a rhyme is good.&#xA;Avoid all shrouds and sometimes&#xA;repetition too. Subtract words&#xA;as needed, maybe all of them.&#xA;Keep one ear close to the page&#xA;and listen&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;to the heartbeat&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;of every word, every space,&#xA;every line; see how lines&#xA;define&#xA;and break&#xA;and keep steady the pace&#xA;of a poem. And remember that&#xA;heart is at the center of it all.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Birds</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/poems/04-06-23-birds/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>//localhost:1313/poems/04-06-23-birds/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;One moment I’m a philosopher, all words&#xA;and fat with truth. The next I’m a poet&#xA;moonlighting for something new to say.&#xA;I’ve tried on the certainty of equations&#xA;since they promised me the last word.&#xA;But I liked the birds instead, every word&#xA;of theirs a spell that guarantees&#xA;the truth of my existence,&#xA;that truths are truisms&#xA;only sometimes true,&#xA;that Truth itself lies&#xA;within and beyond&#xA;what can be said&#xA;and has been said&#xA;with words.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Oranges</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/poems/04-04-23-oranges/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>//localhost:1313/poems/04-04-23-oranges/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;What&amp;rsquo;s real&#xA;is not&#xA;ideal.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Peel&#xA;an orange&#xA;&amp;amp; feel&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;its parts,&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;how easily&#xA;the whole&#xA;breaks&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;apart&#xA;&amp;amp; still&#xA;retains&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;its tart,&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;perfection&#xA;an orange&#xA;in every bite.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Boxelder bugs</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/poems/03-11-23-boxelder/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 11 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>//localhost:1313/poems/03-11-23-boxelder/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Like life, you kept finding your way through my&#xA;walls despite how many times I squished you&#xA;nudged you onto paper mail to leave you&#xA;out in the harsh winter air, where confused&#xA;you wondered what happened to the warmth of&#xA;a home that once housed your black-red body.&#xA;You looked at me with curiosity&#xA;the other day as I was about to&#xA;sweep you away. You crawled along the top&#xA;of my couch, and when I approached you turned&#xA;your body, antennae, and zigzagged legs&#xA;at me as if you knew what was coming.&#xA;In a funny way you give my days shape&#xA;consistency in my daily motions&#xA;meaning I am not creative in how&#xA;I get rid of you from my empty flat&#xA;always with guilt and a pinch of remorse&#xA;because you are there during lonely nights&#xA;in the vents, hiding in the windowsill,&#xA;always available like morning light&#xA;to spring me from my longing, to wake me&#xA;into something just beyond the outline&#xA;of my well-known interiorities.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The meaning in the sea</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/posts/23-03-07-meaning-sea/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>//localhost:1313/posts/23-03-07-meaning-sea/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://images.unsplash.com/photo-1523486230352-65ff5222cea4?crop=entropy&amp;amp;cs=tinysrgb&amp;amp;fit=max&amp;amp;fm=jpg&amp;amp;ixid=MnwzMDAzMzh8MHwxfHNlYXJjaHwxfHxvY3RvcHVzfGVufDB8fHx8MTY3ODIwNDUyOQ&amp;amp;ixlib=rb-4.0.3&amp;amp;q=80&amp;amp;w=1080&#34; alt=&#34;Masaaki Komori&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Sometimes you read something in a book that is so moving that you can’t help feeling that something in you has literally shifted. This was the effect of chapter 28 of Ray Naylor’s “&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.raynayler.net/&#34;&gt;The Mountain in the Sea&lt;/a&gt;.” The book is, in part (there is so much in here!), an exploration of AI, octopuses (yeah, it’s octopuses, not octopi, due to the Greek origins of the word), and the ends that sentient beings will go to preserve themselves.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In times of distress, the domain of our objective functions are flattened to the sole aim of self-preservation. In the process trust is diminished, aggression and vigilance rises, others become means to an end rather than ends in themselves. Sometimes though, in the trenches of our struggles, we produce art, as if it were a necessity. There are things that must be said given the precariousness of the situation, forms of expression that must come out of us if we are not only to survive, but also retain the soul of our humanity. That may be one function of art, if we are to give it one among its many pluralities.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;An enclave of octopuses are being spied on from a camouflaged vessel. The humans have been tasked to do so in an effort to exploit what they don’t yet know about intelligence. They once believed that the octopus was a creature of solitude, one whose life span is like that of a firework, here and then gone in a brilliant blink in the grand scheme of things.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;What they find is something to the contrary. The cephalopods are also capable of communicating with one another in a form that feels both foreign and familiar to the humans. The octopus at the center is dashing off symbols into the oceanic ether. There is repetition and a cadence to the act, and then the humans realize it: the octopus is performing a poem. It’s unclear what it means. But there is something haunting and beautiful to the act as their world is being fished out of existence.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Maybe it all really does boil down to a survival function. But I’d like to think – to believe – that we live for something more, that more is living for something beyond what evolution had in mind. What survives matters. We must look beyond our genes. Beyond our bodies. Beyond utility. Perhaps we must look beyond terraria too and into the umwelt of the other worldly creatures we share a home with.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>To the child reading a book</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/posts/23-03-01-child/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>//localhost:1313/posts/23-03-01-child/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fb2a12fff-623e-4d2c-be85-b500125b43ca_4032x3024.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Sitting across from me is a child with a book in hand. This sort of thing fills me with an unreasonable amount of hope for the world. She’s engrossed by the colors and a sea of static faces, as if in rebellion against the digital ocean designed to captivate us more than the ocean itself. We are drowning in the currents of the former, without any sense of beauty and movement from the latter. Fully garbed in pink, she’s delighting in showing her mother and her mother’s friend the simple happenings that populate the pages. The words are animating her young mind and soul. Her voice has filled the entirety of the café, as she bounces between being herself and the seeming fictions. The line between the two is fuzzier than we think. I don’t want to moralize, but I feel that the parents are doing something right. I see it in the ease of the child’s laugh, the joy that spreads across her lips as she plays in the ocean of her imagination. It’s thanks to her that I feel my younger self has been freed to dive aimlessly into The Mountain in the Sea, to meander in a world inspired by our own.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>baby making in progress</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/posts/23-02-23-babymaking/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>//localhost:1313/posts/23-02-23-babymaking/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F0541f81a-354a-4e85-97e3-727e3a4d6f16_4032x3024.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;There is delight in the way our minds find spurious associations between things. I was looking out the window of a coffee shop at a heap of snow recently formed by an overnight storm, when suddenly my eye caught it: a small white dot on the window, and above it, a trail following a sud of soap. “Baby making in progress” was my first thought. Baby making in progress. I rolled my eyes and laughed at myself. Jesus, I thought. He would be disappointed. I was then brought back to high school health class, which reminded me of the young female teacher my friends and I oogled on the daily like helpless puppies. I don’t think we learned much in that class, but I do remember how strange it was to watch the movie on baby making. You know the one. Heavily pixelated, generic voiceover, 1990s feel to it. We, the freshmen, were deemed mature enough, supposedly, to bear witness to the miraculous, complex machinery of our collective conception. I watched, mesmerized, as animated swarms of sperm raced shoulder to shoulder in an attempt to create new life, to give themselves over for the continuation of our species. Not all of them would make it the narrator said with dramatic indifference. But, as if it were inevitable, there would be an eventual winner. There had to be, he said. That’s the promise of obsessive single-mindedness, singularity of purpose. All they ‘wanted’ to do, all they ‘lived’ for (how lovely and unavoidable our tendency to anthropomorphize) was this. And, perhaps, to stun naive, unlearned high schoolers in Southern California. I was a hopelessly lost child who knew only of video games and brotherhood. That was life, just me and the boys (though sometimes girls were involved too). But perhaps I wasn’t so different from the little swimmers that trained day in and day out within the confines of my developing body. They were my first clue that you didn’t need much to get far in life. All you needed, maybe, was intention and the willingness to swim. How delightful it is then that I am where I am, a decade and a half later, giving thanks to gravity, a watermark, a dried up soap sud, and the beautiful machinations that animate our minds.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dogs</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/posts/23-02-22-dogs/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>//localhost:1313/posts/23-02-22-dogs/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://images.unsplash.com/photo-1610266784664-c60b5dbf0425?crop=entropy&amp;amp;cs=tinysrgb&amp;amp;fit=max&amp;amp;fm=jpg&amp;amp;ixid=MnwzMDAzMzh8MHwxfHNlYXJjaHwxMnx8ZG9nJTIwY29mZmVlJTIwc2hvcHxlbnwwfHx8fDE2NzcwODE1ODc&amp;amp;ixlib=rb-4.0.3&amp;amp;q=80&amp;amp;w=1080&#34; alt=&#34;Photo by Jojo Yuen (sharemyfoodd)&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In Burlington you will find a dog waiting for you around every corner. Try to hide on Hyde Street and you will eventually be barked at by Foxy the coyote-looking dog. Pop into Kru Coffee and ten of them will be waiting in line with you for your daily drip. You cannot escape them when you’re out and about in the city wilds, and that is a good thing, a very good thing.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I want to thank the humans that accompany them for being the kind of people who are willing to raise a dog, or at least for letting me, a petless, heady person, be a beneficiary of their desire and capacity to care for something other than ourselves. These folks are the public servants of joy, even if sometimes they themselves are joyless. To these individuals I am sorry for not acknowledging this, the invisible pain you sometimes carry, but your dog is way too cute for me to notice. I am a sponge for vicarious delight and want to soak up every ounce of happiness produced by your four-legged fur baby. Most of you, though, seem pretty happy.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Today one ran up to me while I was sitting at my usual table with my usual thoughts at my usual coffee shop. He stared at me for a good few seconds, and in those seconds, I felt as if he could see straight through the armor I wear. The curls covering his eyes, his scrappy disposition, all of it was enough to bring me into a weightless reverie. My worries dissipated as the moment focused in on the singularity between us. When he returned to the side of his human to receive his daily treat, I remembered what can come of surrender.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Snow</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/posts/23-02-20-snow/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>//localhost:1313/posts/23-02-20-snow/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F5298a421-2ad7-4178-bcaa-e4012e6353b7_4032x3024.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Snow: so much like sand. The way it clumps, every molecule hanging together, shaped by the objects it falls on, are nothing without the whole. Its individual motes are sparkly and luminous under certain slants of sunlight. Much like us, they rely on the sun for their beauty. Snow and sand form deserted deserts in the night, free from the people and light that gave them attention. Who are we without the eye of another? Is the existence of everything instantiated by—dependent on—the existence of everything else?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Snow is formed by the lack of movement, molecules of water no longer repulsing, each attracted to the other by forces outside their control. These forces lead to its collective dance in the winter, the way it spreads over the land, trees, branches, windows, windshields. Like germs and pollen you can’t shield yourself from its consuming embrace, try as you might. With it comes the cold that pierces our layers, reminds us what it means to be alive, that life requires a certain degree of exposure, a level of vulnerability to what is outside our control. One morning it’s a winter wonderland, the next a sea of gray slush, an inconvenience for the commuters, though the birds don’t seem to mind. They continue to sing despite the weather.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The first time I saw snow I was in Times Square. It was my first time in New York City. Each drop was illuminated by buzzing signs and large billboards. Faces and feet blurred past me as I stood against time with with my body turned toward a sky dotted by snow. Snow, more sticky than the pixels we feed ourselves on. Snow, that reminder of change and seasons, that there is beauty in the extremes. Snow, the seasonal friend of rocks and graveyards who always returns. It always does.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The wooden table I always sit at</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/posts/23-02-18-table/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 18 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>//localhost:1313/posts/23-02-18-table/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I am sitting at a café (so French and proper of me to include the accent over the e) that I frequently visit, a black coffee and The Book of Delights in hand. Ross Gay is a genius and delight. Every word of his makes me smile. (So wonderful that words can do such a thing!) I’d like to meet him and see the world through his eyes. His book is the next best option. Right now the sun is beaming through the window, windows I’ve gazed through countless times, as snow melts from the grooves of the rooftop above me. Who am I telling this to you ask? You, the precious table I always sit at. How many others have spilled coffee upon your surface? How many crumbs of biscuit and croissant have you yourself tasted, each colored by the mouth of tasty, chatty, quiet, solemn strangers, lovers and potential lovers, people with fates yet decided, all over your solid body, a catchall for leftovers and conversation and contemplation? Every day is new to you, even when it’s me and my crumbs again. Familiarity doesn’t scare you. All you need is attention, because despite all appearances, you are quite neglected, though it doesn’t make you too unhappy if you had to be honest, especially those split seconds when the barista is in the bathroom and the patrons are out and off to do something responsible with themselves (like work and taxes), leaving you to bask in the sun and silence, right until the door opens again and a stranger like me sits with you, perhaps to write out these exact thoughts, which are to be enjoyed over other surfaces, in beds, on screens, with coffee and a biscuit perhaps, over other wooden tables somewhere else in the world.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Debate and Dialogue</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/posts/23-02-10-dialogue/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>//localhost:1313/posts/23-02-10-dialogue/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I’ve felt combative recently whenever a new view or idea that differed from my own was presented to me. I’d catch myself feeling this way but would then be too preoccupied with the residue of my self-frustration to course correct in real time. The result was that I learned and contributed less than I could have had my stance been more open and curious, less debate-y, more dialogic.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Maybe this is a consequence of my brief stint as an academic. In constantly having to defend and justify my research, I learned that it’s easier to break things down than to build them up. Regardless, it’s not the most pleasant or fruitful way of being. It tends to leave you with a bitter taste in your mouth, a sense of what’s wrong and problematic but no clarity as to what could be.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Rhetoric is the rule rather than actual conversation in debates. The motivation is to crush your opponent, ideally in style and wit, to outplay the other in a game of verbal jiujitsu while defending your tightly held views. Learning is secondary to winning, and you tend to become more mired in what you already believe.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Conversely, in dialogue, everyone is on the same team. People build off of each other with the intent of creating something more beautiful, something no one could have done on their own. The conversations can still be heated, but they’re engaged in with the understanding that it’s part of something shared. The winners are those who keep playing through their ongoing participation. It’s a game that never ends.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;There’s a place for debate, like, in actual debates. But I’d wager that we’re better off orienting toward dialogues. This might seem too chill for some, but it’s a serious task to be the kind of person who can build and lift others up. The world is already full of people, institutions, and narratives that will try to reduce your soul down to a nub. But if you can keep your light alive and kindle that of others, you’re already ahead of the curve. You can see the exit out of the rat race and want to point others toward it too.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We need more of this, more a sense of vision and possibility, both on a personal and societal level. A lot of people I know are too good at being critical of what we don’t understand, myself included. It’s our defense against against the loneliness and uncertainty, against the creep of collective nihilism and helplessness. Sometimes debating and criticizing is fun and necessary even, but it gets tiring after awhile as a form of engagement with the world. I want to focus on more of what I&amp;rsquo;d like to see, to integrate criticality as a tool that bolsters optimism, not something that diminishes it, as I stray beyond the walls of academia.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Two years of playing guitar</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/posts/guitar/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>//localhost:1313/posts/guitar/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ode to the guitar&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Is it the harsh grief&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;that pours out of you,&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;your thrumming beats, or the&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;                    buzzing of wings:&#xA;is this what I&amp;rsquo;ll recall?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Or are you&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;more thoroughly thrilling&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;in silence,&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;the dove schematized&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;or a woman&amp;rsquo;s hip,&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;a pattern that emerges&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;from its foam&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;and reappears: a turgid, tumbled&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;and resurrected rose.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;from &lt;em&gt;Odes to Common Things&lt;/em&gt;, Pablo Neruda&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;hr&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Two years ago, while visiting my parents for the holidays, I noticed an acoustic guitar in my brother&#39;s room. &lt;em&gt;This is new,&lt;/em&gt; I thought. &amp;quot;Dad got it for me,&amp;quot; he said in a disinterested tone. Curious, I took it back to my room, looked up some &lt;a href=&#34;http://tim.blog/2012/12/11/how-to-play-the-guitar/&#34;&gt;guitar basics&lt;/a&gt;, and began to play with it. My fingers pulsed with pain and self-hatred by the end of the hour, but a new world had opened up for me.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Shortly after returning to Vermont, a pandemic took storm. This prompted my lab to halt data collection, leaving me alone with long stretches of unoccupied time. I had taken the guitar home, but sadly it had been neglected up until this point. I had tried to learn too much at once&amp;mdash;chords, scales, triads&amp;mdash;when what I needed was something simpler, a focus on building immediate confidence and consistency. The key was diving straight into songs.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I started with &lt;em&gt;Georgia&lt;/em&gt; by Vance Joy and fell in love with fingerstyle guitar. Think &lt;em&gt;Stop This Train&lt;/em&gt; by John Mayer, &lt;em&gt;Bloom&lt;/em&gt; by The Paper Kites, &lt;em&gt;I Will Follow You Into the Dark&lt;/em&gt; by Death Cab for Cutie. It felt richer and more melodic than songs dominated by traditional strumming (which I later learned has its own subtle beauty and stylistic complexity). I had more fun playing this way too, despite the upfront difficulties. Perhaps from years of PC gaming, my fingers felt arthritic and clumsy as they each struggled to produce sound. But it got better the more I practiced.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;What kept me going was the joy of witnessing consistent progress. Difficult song progressions and impossible chord shapes always became less so with time and effort. I would often wake up the next day and feel that my fingers were more fluid, my mind and body more relaxed when I practiced again. And soon enough the songs were mine. They weren&#39;t free from blemishes and technical mistakes, but they were my own. Sound had become music.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%253A%252F%252Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%252Fpublic%252Fimages%252Fa69d22e4-6e18-46b9-a811-6bae0eac0fbc_785x544.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;Chop Suey!&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Song tutorials start to feel unsatisfying after a certain point. You still want to do exactly what that one musician on &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=9hxpiFn1DQU&#34;&gt;YouTube&lt;/a&gt; can do, their heads and bodies bobbing in unison with the flight of their nimble fingers across the fretboard. But you also want to know, like, &lt;em&gt;how and why does it all work&lt;/em&gt;? &lt;em&gt;How does everything fit together the way it does?&lt;/em&gt; You want to close down the open chords, break free from the cage of the CAGED system, go full System of a Down, and Rage Against the Machine of tutorial land.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This happened around the year mark for me. I had a few crowd pleasers up my sleeve&amp;mdash;augmented by my preference for everything fingerstyle&amp;mdash;but I had no sense of musicality, no feel for what was possible, no voice or groove of my own. I could play songs and noodle a tiny bit, but I sensed that there was much more to music than my ability to reproduce a song (duh). A return to the basics was needed. Theory, drills, strumming, picking, rhythm, ear training, listening. All necessary ingredients in developing as a musician of any caliber.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I had trouble with this because I had no idea how far I wanted to take my play. The guitar had become a refuge, a spiritual practice of sorts that centered me in difficult times, but I had no burning desire to be a musician. At the end of the day though I felt the nagging urge to improve. I wanted to understand and speak the language of music, even if it meant I had to babble for awhile. It brought me so much joy, so why not go deeper?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;That&#39;s where I&#39;m at now, two years later. I continue to learn songs from YouTube tutorials and have more music theory under my guitar strap. I have a couple of songs and melodies of my own too. The guitar feels less foreign, though I suspect it will forever remain a beautiful, humbling enigma. Brilliant musicians intuit the theory they need as they play, record, and perform. But the rest of us&amp;mdash;the hobbyists and amateurs&amp;mdash;need to learn (and practice) it daily, slowly, deliberately. Even &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=U-MAYC4k15Y&#34;&gt;Tomo&lt;/a&gt; Fujita&amp;mdash;John Mayer&#39;s guitar teacher&amp;mdash;drills the chromatic scale every morning before practice.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In the process you will stumble and drop your pick in the belly of your guitar for the millionth time, leading you to shake it overhead with the unconstrained fury of an adolescent gamer (oh, the poor poor guitar). Self-doubt will be a constant companion, but so too will grace and humility. Why keep going you might ask yourself when you will never be as good as John Mayer, John Butler, Jing Lin, Sungha Jung.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Because, some days, all it takes is a single note to bring you home. To make you feel safe, heard, understood, like all is right with the world. Some days those notes string themselves together and form something that awakens a dormant part of you. And then, if you&#39;re listening, your heart begins to sing.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;hr&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;How it started (around March-April 2020, Georgia by Vance Joy). I struggled so hard with this haha:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;iframe width=&#34;100%&#34; height=&#34;350&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/sHlXgeCXoMI&#34; title=&#34;YouTube video player&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allow=&#34;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;How it&#39;s going (short practice session, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=oTQyofHm3cw&amp;amp;list=RDMM&amp;amp;start_radio=1&#34;&gt;Like a Star&lt;/a&gt; by Youngso Kim). Still struggling, but with much more complex songs!:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;iframe width=&#34;100%&#34; height=&#34;350&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/MoQwODagTng&#34; title=&#34;YouTube video player&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allow=&#34;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Update Feb 3, 2023: Full version below:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;iframe width=&#34;100%&#34; height=&#34;350&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/DhCz4uHYDgU&#34; title=&#34;YouTube video player&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allow=&#34;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&#xA;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Seeds: Looking back on 2020</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/posts/seeds-2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>//localhost:1313/posts/seeds-2020/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;//localhost:1313/images/gallery/seeds4.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;When I think about the past year, I see a child clad in the slowness of seasons, walking the same path by the same lake in the same woods over and over again, searching for something solid to hang onto, comfort in the familiarity of dirt roads, dressed trees, and footsteps perhaps, certainly meaning, in the face of a reality that has just turned dream-like. Sometimes he stops to skip rocks across the water, hoping they will carry his worries with them. He doesn’t know where he’s going, only that he must keep going.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;hr&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This year has been one of the most challenging to date, for obvious reasons. What wasn’t obvious was the shape that my struggles would take and the arcs created and traversed in attempting to resolve them. Given my optimistic nature and proclivity for solitary endeavors, I initially treated news of the pandemic as an opportunity of sorts on the personal front; the impending solitude would serve as the bedrock of my creative muse, the social restrictions a chance to explore and deepen the relationship I had with myself.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This buoyed optimism lasted for a month, tops. What I didn’t anticipate was the necessary reconfiguration of what would give me meaning in the longer days to come when the world finally shut itself down. Plans to visit family for the holidays, hiking the Tour du Mont Blanc prior to starting graduate school, seeing and sending my penpal Alyona off before she returned to Russia; everything had to be cancelled. The degradation of meaning became most visceral in the weeks my lab began transitioning to remote work after our research was put on pause. The emptied office rooms, the reassuring goodbyes shrouding the uncertainty of future reunion, computer screens left vacant in the dark. The architecture that once held up my life was collapsing, and nothing threatens our existence more than the loss of meaning and the emptiness of boredom.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;With a lack of replacements for my usual affairs and the things I looked forward to, I resorted to pastime comforts: video games – League of Legends in particular. But it wasn’t as fun as it used to be. It certainly didn’t provide the same meaning that it once did when I was a decent player trying to make it big in the then emerging e-sports scene. I then started slacklining, practiced guitar more seriously, wrote many poems, and began rollerblading again (after 16-17 years?). Put another way, I was trying to do something productive, but it felt contrived at times, like I was distracting myself from the truth that I was flailing in deep waters, with the shoreline nowhere near in sight.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;//localhost:1313/images/gallery/seeds5.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I also didn’t anticipate how lonely some days would be. Part of this was due to the fact that I was becoming a stranger to myself in that I was adopting new habits, hobbies, and ways of thinking about and interacting with the world, which is always, at least initially, a disciplined pursuit rather than a natural process. Though some days were just painfully lonely too, both physically in how far I felt from people, and mentally in the implications of a civilization being forced to confront its own mortality under the knuckle of dumb politics and a ravenous coronavirus.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Many emotional conversations with friends I fell out of touch with after college soon followed. One in particular stirred me to the bone. We were close, but it had been five years since we last spoke. We reminisced about the first time we met in Applied Psychology, about the meditation program we both participated in later that summer, about the friendship we once had. After mentioning that I had a huge crush on her that year, she revealed that there were many things she should have but did not say to me: that she was in a physically abusive relationship, that her relationship with her family was fragmented, that she struggled with drug abuse, that she lived out of her car for a period after graduation, that suicide had nearly taken her life on multiple occasions.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;//localhost:1313/images/gallery/seeds6.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We were always able to get deep about life, but never too deep, vulnerable, but never enough to be truly seen. I took her hesitation as a sign that we were to remain platonic friends, but never as a consequence of inner turmoil. Things were better now she said. She’s in a supportive relationship and is pursuing a nursing degree. But she had never told her story to anyone before, not even to her current partner. I was the first to hold it, and this time the tears came.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Catching tears. It certainly gives me meaning.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;//localhost:1313/images/gallery/seeds7.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;If I’ve learned anything in the midst of this year, it’s that we need each other more than we can ever realize, at all scales. Us students in the complex systems program are trained to quantify, model, and interrogate the implications of this idea – the interconnected nature of things – but you only need to have retained a bit of your child-like imagination to feel the tide of a world stitched together by infinitely many threads.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The most jarring cascade following the onset of the pandemic has been that of how we experience time. Our [days, weeks, months] are less eventful in the usual sense, and therefore lack the glue, the stories and moments, that would have otherwise distinguished one [day, week, month] from the next. A consequence of this is that it becomes difficult to remember, well, anything. Memories require context, from which meaning is construed.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This collective amnesia was another contributing factor to my growing sense of isolation, leading me to spend more time inhabiting online spaces. They have been a saving grace in many respects, but I can’t help feeling increasingly disembodied the more time I spend on them. Participation in these spaces involves embedding your attention, which is to say your Self (the buddhist in me is speaking), into a timeline that operates on a timescale vastly different from the one we’re capable of processing. Events here occur at a faster rate, often without context (goodbye story, goodbye meaning), and they lack the viscosity of first-hand experience. The result is what feels like lost time, muddled memories, and further fragmentation of the Self.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The realm of the digital isn&amp;rsquo;t going anywhere though, so we will have to find ways to reconcile this personal divide, perhaps by merging into it completely, rebelling against it, or developing new identities that can hold the tension. Who is the person that emerges from these spaces? Surely less of ourselves, but possibly more too. All that we experience shapes us, and we shape all that we experience.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;//localhost:1313/images/gallery/seeds8.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Music and poetry were essential sources of sustenance, as was the generosity of distant friends and the serendipity of the internet. The website that started my friendship with Alyona, Interpals, also led to meeting Sasha, a stranger who became so much more. We often say that we are cut from the same ethereal thread because we just &lt;em&gt;see&lt;/em&gt; each other, despite never having met in person. The half-joke between us is that we’re long lost soulmates, but the truth is, that’s the most accurate way to describe what we have between us: we’ve created a home (sometimes called Our Tower) that is freeing and nourishing to inhabit. Ideas, music, poems, vulnerability, and pictures of her cat are the only valid forms of currency in this space governed by play and imagination.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Marieke, my Camino soulmate, liked the idea of life providing us with people who are disguised as angels when we need their grace the most, only leaving once their duty is done. I think what ties Sasha and I together runs along a similar vein. To me it’s the magic referred to by Celine in The Before Trilogy: “I believe if there&amp;rsquo;s any kind of God it wouldn&amp;rsquo;t be in any of us, not you or me but just this little space in between. If there&amp;rsquo;s any kind of magic in this world it must be in the attempt of understanding someone sharing something. I know, it&amp;rsquo;s almost impossible to succeed but who cares really? The answer must be in the attempt.”&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Soulmate. It&amp;rsquo;s a term we usually reserve for romantic partners, but why not be more imaginative and extend its reach to people who are more than that; to people who touch, sustain, and lift our spirits. We need them now more than ever.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;//localhost:1313/images/gallery/seeds10.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Something else I didn’t expect this year was how much I would like being a graduate student. I remember telling the PhD-toting Sasha (and my boss, the PI of my study, at one point) early on in the semester that I wanted to quit. But she reminded me that fear often speaks loudest when confronted with difficulty, and nudged me in her quiet way to continue.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;It’s challenging, yes – I wondered daily if I was cut out for all the math and research papers and struggled virtually all the way through the first semester – but that’s the case for most things worth doing; life&amp;rsquo;s challenges are fertile ground for meaning. In the most defining instances you have to parent yourself and become your own hope-generating, meaning-making machine. Not of the rosy, frivolous type, but of the resilient, pragmatic you-can-do-this-and-have-overcome-similar-challenges-so-shut-up-and-stop-doubting-yourself type.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“I write to discover meaning,” the poet Louise Glück once noted. “Nothing should be wasted. Something must come of it. And writing is a kind of revenge against circumstance. Bad luck, loss, pain — if you make something out of it, then you’ve no longer been bested by these events.” How we move through – because we can never get over – the heart of uncertainty demands more of us. It demands retreat, rest, and recalibration of the compasses that no longer serve us. It demands us to continue writing, to take revenge against circumstance, to make something out of nothing.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The boy, clad in the slowness of seasons, will continue to walk the same path by the same lake in the same woods over and over again, though the rocks in his fists have transformed into seeds, seeds yearning for soil, seeds beckoning for home, seeds hungry for the forlorn.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;//localhost:1313/images/gallery/hangon.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Special thanks&lt;/em&gt;: Shirley, Alyona, Sasha, Eszter, Mom &amp;amp; Dad, Paulina, Mandy, El, Avery, Sam, Olivia, Julia, Cheryl, Alesha, Shana, Corey, Naz, the random people I met while slacklining, and the ABCD crew for the gift of presence and memories.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;hr&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Lists for myself, to compensate for the fallibility of memory in 2020&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h1 id=&#34;timeline-of-notable-things&#34;&gt;Timeline of notable things&lt;/h1&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Dad gave me his guitar, first pluck of a string: first week of Jan&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Met Alyona in Boston for the first time: &lt;a href=&#34;https://philintheblank.me/blog/2020/01/moments/&#34;&gt;Jan 17&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Reconnecting with N: Jan 30&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Acceptance into CSDS graduate prog: Feb 21&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Reconnecting with Corey: ~March&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;NET-COVID Workshop: &lt;a href=&#34;https://philintheblank.me/work/life-after/&#34;&gt;April 16&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Started slacklining: Apr 29&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Started talking to Sasha: May 1&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Moved into own apartment: May 22&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;First Interintellect salon (topic: Refugees): June 11&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Started hanging with Mandy: Jun 27&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Landing my first full backflip: Jul 21&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Hanging out for Joe’s birthday: Jul 26&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Lots of hikes with Avery: scattered across the timeline, somewhere here :)&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Running into Alesha while slacklining, after 2 years?: Aug 23&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;First day of grad school: Aug 31&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Sunrise hike with Shana and DK: Sep 25&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;First poem published: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.icaf.org/ABCDStudy/&#34;&gt;Oct 16&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Interview with VTDigger for holiday season plans: Nov 24&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Thanksgiving Dinner with the neighb, El: Nov 26&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;First ever jam session with Eszter and a hang drum: Nov 28&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;First attempt at writing a song on guitar: Dec 7&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h1 id=&#34;words-of-affirmation&#34;&gt;Words of affirmation&lt;/h1&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;your poems are pure magic. they are sewn from the matter that makes me love life.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Have you noticed that us put together in a room is pure groundlessness? You and I could talk about the wonders of the universe until we’ve reached complete exhaustion and utter depletion from being so full.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“…what is your superpower? Your whole being is a cure for loneliness…truly. Like how you listen to people, it&amp;rsquo;s medicine for the soul. That deep understanding and great wish to understand the other. That supportive and positive state of mind you are in, the way you&amp;rsquo;re always smiling. And even when you are in a deep deep sadness, you can be at your best and cheer everybody up and pull them up to your level…it&amp;rsquo;s something which is really unique.”&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h1 id=&#34;books-poems-thoughts-that-nourished-me&#34;&gt;Books, poems, thoughts that nourished me&lt;/h1&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Wild Geese, Mary Oliver&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Possibilities, Wisława Szymborska&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;320 (There’s a certain Slant of light,), Emily Dickinson&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;632 (The Brain – is wider than the Sky –), Emily Dickinson&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Just Beyond Yourself, David Whyte&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.brainpickings.org/2020/10/21/14-years-of-brain-pickings/&#34;&gt;Choose Joy&lt;/a&gt;, Maria Popova&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;books&#34;&gt;Books&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;David Whyte, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.brainpickings.org/2015/04/29/david-whyte-consolations-words/&#34;&gt;Consolations&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Already Free, Bruce Tift&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The Fear of Doing Nothing, Valery Hazanov&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Transcend, Scott Barry Kaufman&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;music&#34;&gt;Music&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Nightwish&lt;/strong&gt;: helmed by Floor Jansen, greatest, most versatile singer alive. Beautiful, lyrical, symphonic performances.&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;You have such &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=N4Vfy5yCy-c&#34;&gt;oceans within&lt;/a&gt;&amp;hellip;&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ut6ufu2CPNg&#34;&gt;Mama mia&lt;/a&gt;&amp;hellip;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=yYtkPpFYzOo&#34;&gt;The heart is better&lt;/a&gt;, thanks to you&amp;hellip;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;I love you &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=1fu-yP6q6Gk&#34;&gt;Floor&lt;/a&gt;&amp;hellip;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Aurora&lt;/strong&gt;: the outcome of a childhood unhindered.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;City of the Sun&lt;/strong&gt;: freedom.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Coldplay&lt;/strong&gt;: life.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;John Mayer&lt;/strong&gt;: everything between.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Civil Wars&lt;/strong&gt;: slow dancing.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;John Paul White&lt;/strong&gt;: the hurting kind.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ólafur Arnalds&lt;/strong&gt;: meditations on solitude.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sungha Jung&lt;/strong&gt;: inspiration.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;hr&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;ve come (read) this far, thank you. Keep going. &amp;lt;3&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Feelings</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/posts/feelings/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 06 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>//localhost:1313/posts/feelings/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Feelings are fleeting by nature, like the passage of clouds on a warm summer day.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Though too often we wear them like immutable masks and declare, &amp;ldquo;This is me. This is all I will ever be.&amp;rdquo; Sad. Resentful. Despondent. Happy. In truth they are masks, transient facades that hide a more true and vulnerable sense of self.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We put these masks on when we&amp;rsquo;re scared, when we&amp;rsquo;re too afraid to ask for attention and love; when we&amp;rsquo;re on the verge of breaking, but don&amp;rsquo;t know how to ask for help. When we&amp;rsquo;re in search of something solid in the face of groundlessness. Even happiness is something we try too hard to hold onto, strangling it of all significance in the process.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Feelings are signals: they point toward ourselves, toward the unknown. But they are not us.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;To take this non-attached perspective is more terrifying than the feelings themselves; we would rather feel angry and sad than risk being a lonely drop in the ocean. &amp;ldquo;Yet what is an ocean but a multitude of drops?&amp;rdquo; Non-attachment is not detachment. Detaching is active avoidance whereas non-attachment is active engagement––detachment runs while non-attachment sits and feels and notices with non-judgment.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;From the vantage of non-attachment, we can see our feelings as they truly are: simply feelings, waves that come and go like the seasons; things as permanent as the illusory grounds they stand upon.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Then who are we if not our feelings? What is under the mask? What is left?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We are something else entirely, something both more and less grounded, a shifting paradox, something wildly, unconditionally beautiful.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We are the calm after a storm.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;A newborn&amp;rsquo;s first breath.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Tiny motes of existence.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;A beam piercing through the darkness.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The light of Being.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Proof of grace.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Lucky.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Free.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
