<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Psychedelics on Phil in the Blank</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/categories/psychedelics/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Psychedelics on Phil in the Blank</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 21 Jun 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
      <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/categories/psychedelics/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>On psychedelics and change</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/23-06-21-psych-change/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Jun 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/23-06-21-psych-change/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fb3fa0c7b-896c-43b4-bdbb-581f4eb9231a_3024x4032.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;📷: Lion’s mane jellyfish I saw at the New England Aquarium!&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Hi friends!&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;A friend recently asked me how my experience on psychedelics have changed me, relative to other major events in my life. This is a hard question to answer, partly because it feels like comparing apples to the Andromeda galaxy. There are way too many variables that would confound a meaningful comparison (apples man!), especially when it comes to a psychedelic trip and, say, my &lt;a href=&#34;https://philintheblank.me/posts#category=Camino&#34;&gt;journey&lt;/a&gt; across the Camino de Santiago. I’ve also only taken them twice, each time with a moderate to high dose for the purpose of personal insight, which is to say I am no veteran of the psychonautic landscape. But I’ll try to provide a tentative answer to what I think is at the heart of the question: how have psychedelics affected my life?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(All the usual caveats regarding psychedelic use stand here. I ain’t a doc and you should not read my words in a prescriptive fashion.)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;hr&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;It’s worth saying at the outset that psychedelics will not solve all of your problems. If you’re facing a difficult decision and/or are seeking to change your life in some significant way, I’d urge you to try addressing these things head-on, first. Travel, read books, talk to people, &lt;strong&gt;do&lt;/strong&gt; things differently, patiently experiment, seek your own answers to the &lt;a href=&#34;https://philintheblank.substack.com/p/live-the-questions&#34;&gt;questions&lt;/a&gt; tugging at your soulstrings. Find out what’s behind your desire to use psychedelics and see if you might be able to satisfy it without their use. Committing to this ongoing project will change you! At the very least you will become more intentional about using them, all the while cultivating your sense of personal agency.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Maybe I’m old school (PSA: apparently 29 is the new 30, ha..!), but I mention this because people tend to avoid the work and devotion that meaningful change requires, even when they’re aware of what they need to do. It’s a long and difficult road, so we sometimes distract ourselves with social media, mindless hook-ups, disembodied philosophies, and grandiose spirituality quests. (Yes God can be a distraction.) This is fine at times. You do not need to constantly Work On Yourself. But know that psychedelics can be a distraction too, one that can make you drastically worse off, especially at the dosages that mediate lasting change. Under their power, you may feel ready to leap into the void, only to later realize that you left your parachute behind because it was ruining the vibe.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I’ve used psychedelics before to help me decide whether or not to continue a relationship I was struggling with. On the surface everything seemed fine: I was creatively engaged; I was in good health; I was doing proper grad school things; I was supported in my relationship. But I was also so, so lonely. I felt directionless, incompetent, disconnected from my peers and my work, unsure of myself and what I wanted. I knew I had to change something about how I was living, but it felt like the foundation of my life would crumble if I did.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;And it did, not long after the trip. My intention was to understand why I felt so much pain and disconnection when we were together, and to discover a way forward. What came up instead was an indecipherable hurricane of emotions. There was anger, frustration, guilt, shame, resentment, a lack of acceptance, and self-flagellation. There was also warmth, love, affection, and gratitude, too. At some point I tried to play a song on my guitar, only to find that the entirety of my conscious being was content on riding the ethereal reverberations of a single C-shaped D Major chord. This was not part of the Plan.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Later I went down to the lake to process the experience. It didn’t reveal anything about what I should do, not really anyways. All I knew was that there was a deep conflicting pain inside of me that arose within the context of our relationship. Parts of me wanted to continue, while others wanted to leave.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We broke up a few days later. I felt okay about it as long as I was working or engaged in activity. But the grief welled up inside of me. And then it overcame me like a great, all-consuming wave, one I kept drowning under over and over again. Suddenly academic research felt meaningless. Similarly with writing, exercising, going outside, playing the guitar—everything that once held my life up. A month goes by, and on the drive from my friend’s wedding–which I officiated–I realized that I needed help as I imagined, through merciless tears, what it’d be like if I suddenly drove off the edge of the 89.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F068ebe88-93dc-4c5d-aeb7-94716e88444d_4032x3024.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;After the wedding, I took a few weeks off from working on my PhD and stayed with my parents in California. Being away from Vermont made me realize how misplaced I felt in academia. It was the available and appealing path, one encouraged by my wonderful lab members, but I did not want to &lt;a href=&#34;https://philintheblank.substack.com/p/i-left-my-phd&#34;&gt;walk&lt;/a&gt; it. A close friend I trusted gave me heartfelt advice and difficult feedback around the same time. It came from a place of genuine concern and compassion, but I was not ready to hear it yet. Any idle moment I had was immediately filled with heaviness and despair, leaving me feeling helpless and trapped. I felt unhinged and alone and afraid that things would never improve.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Some of my friend’s wisdom must have seeded itself in me though. This, alongside the small but ongoing support of friends and parents, gave me enough inertia to begin helping myself. And then, eventually, I got lucky. I landed a job that allowed me to leave my PhD. I made more proximate friends and widened my circle of social engagement. I reconnected with my ex. (Things ended again later, but on a better note.) I rekindled my creative spirit. (Thank you &lt;a href=&#34;https://notes.ellenrhymes.com/RRR&#34;&gt;RRR&lt;/a&gt;, Dialogic Circle, and others!) I sought more help. I started recognizing what was important to me and acted on it. And I got better, bit by bit.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;hr&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The brain seems to become more malleable after psychedelic use, meaning it’s easier for new patterns of thought and behavior to form and settle. This is usually framed in a positive light, but it’s possible that the changes run the other way too. In my case, the post-trip/post-breakup pit I found myself in was potentially deepened by the intensity of my grief and depression. If true, it suggests that extreme care should be taken when considering psychedelically-mediated life changes. It could have gone much worse than it did, and I recommend against making such big changes all at once, at least not without support, nor without having exhausted other options.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Truthfully, what I needed was a robust structure in place to help me transition through the major life decisions I was contemplating. I needed a close friend or two who was consistent and physically there for me; a good therapist, perhaps; work and activity that felt meaningful; a large dose of courage, and the momentum of baby steps.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In a sense then, psychedelics kind of ruined my life. They enabled me to make a decision about the relationship and later my PhD, but I was unprepared for the immensity of the losses and everything else that quickly followed. In another sense, they saved me. They made me more sensitive and receptive to the signals radiating from my body. They wiped off the smudge marks from my inner compass and revealed the urgency of the work ahead. It’s true that, sometimes, one has to &lt;a href=&#34;https://sashachapin.substack.com/p/in-praise-of-blowing-up-your-life&#34;&gt;completely uproot&lt;/a&gt; their lives and go through hell in order to build a better one, for every person involved.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;When I decided to walk the Camino, it was not an answer to a call for adventure exactly, but rather a lack of options and the necessity of the moment. I had read about it in a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.perseusbooks.com/titles/kamal-ravikant/rebirth/9780316312257/&#34;&gt;story&lt;/a&gt; and told myself I would walk it one day in the far future. Well, that day came much sooner than I expected. I was working at a summer camp in Maine and had just been denied a job I wanted for when camp ended. Days later, feeling liminal while drifting alone in the middle of a lake on a paddle board, the idea to trek across Spain came to me. It was more a suggestion than a compelling vision, one that was incredibly far-fetched and impractical, but I knew it was what I had to do. I didn’t know how I was going to do it, but I paddled back to shore and immediately booked a one-way ticket to Europe.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;There I met some very wonderful people. I stuffed my face with Spanish Tortillas. I deepened my felt understanding of love and joy. I began to write more seriously. I fell in love with my &lt;a href=&#34;https://philintheblank.me/posts/14c-letters-soulmate/&#34;&gt;Camino soulmate&lt;/a&gt;. I ran out of money. But there were still parts of me that felt just as lost as I did prior to the journey when I came back home. I still had to figure out where I wanted to live, how to earn an income, and so on, all of which was constrained by a budding sense of urgency (and a negative bank account). I’d been thinking about pursuing a PhD in clinical psychology even before Spain, and this was what I thought I still wanted to do, which led me to Vermont, my home for the past five years. Now I have a masters degree in complex systems and data science, lol.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;So, Spain changed me I think, but I can’t really tell you how. In many ways I feel like I’m the same person as I was prior to the walk. That’s how I kind of feel now regarding my experience with psychedelics. Perhaps these experiences have allowed me to become more me, which is sadly not always an easy feat. All I feel certain about is that change is hard. And it’s hard not because we resist change itself, but &lt;a href=&#34;https://haleynahman.substack.com/p/voice-note-changing-your-life-without#details&#34;&gt;something else&lt;/a&gt; beneath the surface.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Psychedelics can help you dig beneath the surface and untangle the emotional roadblocks that are preventing you from improving your life. They can tease out old patterns of thought and behavior, and make them more amenable to revision and replacement. This is often the work itself and why people turn to psychedelics. But without the proper scaffolding in place, it’s not improbable that you may fall back into the old patterns you were hoping to change. God may show himself to you, but what will you do about it if he tells you to go home? If he wants to know how you will change your life?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In addition to the possibility of revision, we need our earthly visions too, a re-visioning of sorts on a personal and collective level, a concrete sense of where we want to go and who we want to be, if change is to last. Psychedelics can show you what it’s like to feel more connected to yourself, others, and the world, what might be worth aspiring towards. They can open up the door to meaningful change and ease the first steps of a lifelong endeavor. But you will still need to do the work that the universe requires of you when you come back down to Earth. And maybe that work is a stroll across Spain.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Thanks Aly &amp;amp; Shirley for the feedback on this essay.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Into the multiverse</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/22-07-16-multiverse/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 16 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/22-07-16-multiverse/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F8b0b5a7e-3a24-4bcc-80d2-c41825a7c7c7_1041x998.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;Stephan’s Quintet, taken by the James Webb Space Telescope. Attribution: NASA. Something fun to note: The Webb telescope is so sensitive that it can detect the heat signature of a bumblebee at the distance of the Moon (from Earth), and can see details the size of a US penny at the distance of about 25 miles or 40 kilometers!&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The past six months have been covered by a dark, oppressive cloud that made me doubt if I would ever feel good again. I sometimes wondered if life was worth living, and though I quickly extinguished these kinds of thoughts, I had lost faith in my ability to understand how I felt and what I needed to move myself forward. I hated being alone but couldn’t enjoy the company of others. Crying spells came over me at random times throughout the day. Nights were unbearably restless. I felt stuck and lifeless, like a ship without a sail.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Fortunately I’m now starting to come out of it, in no small part thanks to the help of psychedelics. This was my second time taking them (I wrote about my first time &lt;a href=&#34;https://philintheblank.me/posts/trippy/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;) which I approached with three specific intentions: 1) to let go of the shame and feeling of being a failure associated with the end of my relationship, 2) to reflect on my career and desires, and 3) to feel more in touch with life again. I had done a lot of inner work and received an absurd amount of help from family and friends (thank you guys) prior to taking them, though they certainly enhanced and accelerated the healing process.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The rest of this post will highlight parts of the experience and insights (that I remember) I had that seemed to have led me to a better state of mind. It will be more personal and anecdotal since others have already written about the potential benefits and reasons as to why you might want to embark on a similar journey. Disclaimer: I’m only a doctor-in-training, and not the kind that can credibly prescribe medical advice lol. I am in no way suggesting that anyone reading this should use psychedelics for any reason.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;hr&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I woke up early and started the morning with a short stroll around the block to solidify my intentions. Two grams of psilocybin were waiting for me upon my return home. I wasn’t sure what to expect from the trip, but I knew it was important to be open to whatever came up during the experience. Still, a part of me was hanging onto the hope that I would be granted specifically what I asked for: more clarity and a renewed license on life. When the clock struck seven, I lit a candle and began the journey.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;There was nothing for the first hour. No changes in perception, no notable differences in the order and ordinariness of my living room. Then I started feeling irritated. I also noticed the presence of a heavy weight hanging over my head. I wasn’t sure if this was my mind attempting to keep itself intact while being unraveled by the psilocybin, or something else, but I leaned further into it. Slowly my mind states felt less discrete. I became less inhibited as the boundary between the world and my sense of self loosened. Time was losing its grip over reality, and moments started merging together like a continuous fluid I was no longer separate from.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;At one point I picked up my guitar and tried playing a song I knew, but I couldn’t get past the first chord. Each note reverberated with an overwhelming beauty and multitude of meanings that filled every inch of body and left me dumbstruck. Music is so fucking beautiful! It wasn’t long before my mind went down the rabbit hole of other seemingly unrelated thoughts. There was less a sense of control over myself, but I didn’t feel afraid. I wanted to be carried down the current and see what wanted to be shown.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I thought about consciousness and the many layers of story we choose and don’t choose to live by, how they sometimes prevent us from doing certain things and push us toward others, how flexible and amenable they are to change, all while witnessing the recursive and layered nature of self and identity. One moment I would be laughing wildly, the next crying like a helpless infant, though again, the moments didn’t really feel like moments at this point. Thoughts, feelings, and emotions flowed through me the way water does when rushing past stones in a river. There was the constant urge to sense-make, to grasp and understand what by nature never could be. I thought about how absurd we are at times, how absurd society is, how absurd it is that we believe we know anything with certainty. Everything felt connected and meaningful. And then it didn’t. And then it did again.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Later I arrived at thoughts of my relationship. Living in my chest was a sense of being a failure and the fear of failing again in the future. There was a lot of shame too in how things ended, in how I couldn’t overcome myself to keep what should have been enough. I had to keep trying I thought, and in a way I was still trying to make things work for me. I reached out to hold these emotions and began to forgive myself. I recognized that I had tried my best and acknowledged how much pain I was in from trying to prevent the ship from sinking. Waves of ecstasy and sorrow moved through me as I rummaged through old photos, loving text messages, thoughtful memorabilia I had received throughout our relationship. Everything was a reminder of the love that existed and was created by us. There was so much of that, so much love.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I also saw that we were propelled by dreams and fantasies that were beyond our reach. Getting married. Coming home to the safety of each other at the end of the day. Having kids and spending our days learning together. Sharing a quiet life full of our perfectly boring and specific kind of fun and love. It was excruciating to see their beauty, and to let them go. (Writing about them now, I continue to feel their pains echoing across my body, though it’s much less intense than the previous months.) The reality was that something consistently felt off for me, and not listening to that feeling made the relationship more difficult than it had to be. That I could see and was beginning to finally accept. I wanted the love to be enough, but it wasn’t able to bridge our dreams to something more real. What was real was that something wasn’t working for me.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I cried on my couch for the next hour, then laid there with a sleeping mask over my eyes. Colorful geometric patterns with fractal-like structures pulsed in and out of the darkness in a dance with my fleeting feelings and fragmented thoughts. Nothing was really coherent at this point, but the visions induced an unspeakable awe in me. I remember seeing a constellation of bright lights in the center of my mind that put me in a religious trance. It looked like a small cloud or series of sunbeams piercing the void of space, a little bit like the album cover of “Make Yourself” by Incubus. I felt at peace and felt that life was going to be okay.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Some time later, as my mind slowly pieced itself together, I made my way to the kitchen to eat leftover tortilla chips. It was difficult to walk because my sense of myself in space and my connection to my body was still somewhat severed. But I got to the counter soon enough and gathered my delectables. It took several minutes to put one chip in my mouth because I was stupidly astonished by the damn thing. How it was made, its intricate shape, the way it felt between my fingers, the joy it brought to so many people – I was on the verge of tears again. And then I ate it. What followed was virtually an orgasm – a foodgasm. My whole body shook with delight each time my tongue made contact with the chip and tasted what was the golden ratio of salt and lime. Chewing and swallowing was clunky and unappealing like my walk into the kitchen, but still, it was the best damn chip I had ever eaten in my life. Eating is so fucking sensual! I said to myself. (Thinking about the experience now is kinda turning me on lol)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;When I felt more grounded, I went outside and walked downtown toward the lake. There was a lightness in my step and an unfamiliar confidence in the way that I carried myself. I felt less self-centered. My attention was more easily captured by what was happening around me rather than the content of my own thoughts. Everything was fun to look at: flowers, clouds, worms crawling on the ground, porches, sidewalks, people. Who knew it could be so fun to look at the world? I, Mr. budding writer, supposedly did, but I had forgotten how pleasurable it was to give something my fullest attention – no, rather, to have it be completely seized by something beyond myself.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I loved noticing my attention shift from an intensely focused microscope to a softer panoramic view. I couldn’t contain my smile and constantly had the urge to laugh. That was funny to notice: the desire to suppress my emotions in order to come off a certain way. I went to a bookstore to test the state of my cognition, which I found was highly functional if I tried hard enough to read the book I was holding. A computational psychiatry book held my interest for some time, though I grew bored of it pretty quickly. Nothing else in the store really caught my eye either. My motivation to read and tendency toward abstraction had become less existent. All I wanted to do was walk around, look, and experience the moment firsthand. Nothing felt as interesting as what I could perceive.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;hr&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;My girlfriend and I broke up five months ago, but we had continued to try to make things work until very recently. A part of me had wanted the trip to bring us back together, to bring me to a place where I had found a way to keep the relationship alive. But it only showed me more clearly that I had to let her go. I wasn’t anxious about it anymore, just sad, which is perhaps the best state to be in given the circumstances. I still think of her and feel lonely at times, but I know that my letting go came from a place of total acceptance. I have an unwavering faith in that wherever life takes us, it will be a better place. I’m also certain that this was the most loving thing to do, for her and myself.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I’m returning to a certain mood baseline already, which was to be expected, but I also seem more able to trust my instincts. Old compulsions and lackluster habits don’t have as much gravity anymore. The urge to control my experience has been reduced. I feel comfortable in my body again, and there’s more lightness and joy when I go about my day. I feel more content to be who I already am, which is much better than only believing that you are. I find myself quite charming and funny. It’s easier to smile and laugh. I still have my moments when I’m wrapped up in thought, but letting them go comes more effortlessly when the moment warrants it. My emotions are less turbulent, more consistently happy.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;People who know me would say that I was already a happy, optimistic, and care-free person. What they didn’t see was that so much of my existence was also riddled by incessant self-doubt and worry. I never had the sense that I was doing anything right with my life, hence the fear of failure and associated shame with regard to my relationships, my winding career trajectory, and my creative pursuits. They always recognized the potential in me and tried to nurture and encourage it, but I never felt like I was good enough. I never felt like I was enough, not in a viscerally manner anyways. I fully recognize this now and feel confident that I can catch myself if I fall back into the depths of these thought patterns.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;As for my career and desires, I don’t see myself hopping out of the PhD quite yet, or at least I don’t feel as bad about doing it as I did before. It feels more like a job that neatly fits where I’m at in life than a crucial part of my identity and happiness. I also want to write more and focus on honing my creativity. I used to think that my craft was specifically writing, but I’m seeing now that maybe it’s about expression and learning more generally. In my high school years I enjoyed writing guides, coaching newb League of Legends players, streaming my gameplay, and making YouTube videos with my online friends. Later I learned how to code and build websites, math and statistics, and how to grasp the gestalt of difficult subjects. As long as I’m learning and making things that affect even one person, I think I’ll be pretty content. This is something I want to explore more across multiple mediums.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;It will never cease to amaze me that a compound like psilocybin can produce so much clarity, insight, and joy. Obviously I still need to go about living my days and engaging with the world, which is the true testing ground. But I feel all the more prepared for it. The fear of losing the confidence and lightness is real, but I’m guessing that as long as I stay and act within the vicinity of my desires, life will continue to feel good. It’s possible too that at least some of these changes will be more or less permanent. If not, I may have to take the word of my therapist, who cutely said that “people should do psychedelics every six months”, and see again what lies both within and beyond the universe of my mind.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
