<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Delights on Phil in the Blank</title>
    <link>https://philintheblank.me/categories/delights/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Delights on Phil in the Blank</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 30 Aug 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
      <atom:link href="https://philintheblank.me/categories/delights/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>5AM</title>
      <link>https://philintheblank.me/poems/23-08-30-fiveam/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Aug 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://philintheblank.me/poems/23-08-30-fiveam/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I woke up at 5am to make my roommate breakfast because it’s her first day of school as a teacher. Afterwards I couldn’t fall back asleep and began instead to listen to the early morning. It’s a pleasant if not unerring space to be in. It’s just you and the slowness of the hour, held by an awareness of the moment, steeping in the water of creation, wherein the mind remains quiet and ripe. Here nothing is asked of you except, perhaps, to listen.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The sound of a cricket and the no-sound&#xA;of absence. No sense not nonsense,&#xA;only the hushed humming of morning.&#xA;Morning, still with dust in its eyes,&#xA;darkness, wrapping up its shift.&#xA;The birds have begun to rehearse&#xA;while the dead mourn their last drink.&#xA;Thoughts piercing the veil of dreams,&#xA;shadows creeping over the landscape.&#xA;The movement of water&#xA;through pipes and the air unseen.&#xA;My existence made known&#xA;in the quiet clattering of keys.&#xA;Streams of consciousness&#xA;louder than the Winooski river.&#xA;A lonely crow echoing&#xA;in the distance.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A poem for Québec</title>
      <link>https://philintheblank.me/poems/23-08-21-quebec/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Aug 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://philintheblank.me/poems/23-08-21-quebec/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In stillness Québec flowers.&#xA;Like the first shot of espresso&#xA;or your last kiss of the morning&#xA;and perhaps even after&#xA;a perfectly placed line-break,&#xA;its flavor rolls and multiples,&#xA;grows and expands&#xA;the way words and sentences&#xA;do over full-stops and commas,&#xA;the longer you linger.&#xA;So linger a little longer.&#xA;Come to the realization&#xA;that tourists and citizens&#xA;are all the same&#xA;when they meet your gaze&#xA;at the windowpane.&#xA;Listen to how the children speak&#xA;in footsteps and foreign tongues&#xA;and still find each other.&#xA;Notice how even grief&#xA;is content to waif and flâneur&#xA;along the cobble-covered streets.&#xA;Later, when you&amp;rsquo;re meeting someone&#xA;for the first time and their hands&#xA;are already all over you,&#xA;convincing you that&#xA;&lt;em&gt;You are a silly American&lt;/em&gt;&#xA;&lt;em&gt;and this is how we will bridge&lt;/em&gt;&#xA;&lt;em&gt;the distance of language,&lt;/em&gt;&#xA;you are ready to surrender.&#xA;Later, when you&amp;rsquo;re mouthing&#xA;your goodbyes at the bus stop,&#xA;you are ready to depart.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Inspiration &amp; memory</title>
      <link>https://philintheblank.me/posts/23-08-17-inspiration-memory/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Aug 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://philintheblank.me/posts/23-08-17-inspiration-memory/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ff2fc9762-fbf9-4584-a47c-c890ec1aff91_4032x3024.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I was walking out of a coffee shop in Oregon the other day when a tiny brown napkin flew across my feet. What followed was a cascade of memories that brought me back to a particularly creative winter.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;It was the first year of the covid pandemic (and grad school). I was holed up inside my apartment. The days were lonely at times, but also full of aliveness and energy. I sketched, read, wrote, played guitar, and walked around whenever the wind and snow had settled. &amp;ldquo;I could spend most of my days like this,&amp;rdquo; I said to my penpal. We talked about how easy it is to forget things, and then I suddenly remembered the first time I visited New York City.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In particular I recalled walking the streets with a stranger I met on the last day of my trip. I had asked her to watch my luggage for me so that I could buy something from the Bryant Park library gift shop. There were other motives too, frankly: I thought she was attractive and had wanted to talk to her. So young, so bold, so naive—she could have ran with my things!—but we ended up enjoying the city together. We got coffee at a local shop, walked to and through Central Park, shared dreams and stories, and struggled to find a public bathroom, all within the span of three hours. The goodbye was short and sweet, just like her, just like the memory.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I’d always been a shy kid (imagine bookish, bespectacled, Asian gamer) who believed he was unattractive. So it was a big deal for me that the adventure had gone so well. The experience was incredibly formative. And then I forgot about it. When I’d tell people about the time I won a trip to NYC (through a Freakonomics raffle!), the story with the stranger was always omitted. That it had come back while talking to my penpal in the midst of winter, years later, generated some images in mind regarding the nature of memory.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I pictured a kind of book, one with an infinite number of pages containing the full content of our lives. These books were physical, meaning they suffered too as bodies do when held by the hand of time. Ink rotted into dust, pages loosened and floated away with every flick of a page-turn. Retrieving memories was thus like chasing after ghosts and symbols that, when obtained and superimposed on one another, could constitute a life.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Who was doing this busywork of encoding and retrieval? I imagined a ghostwriter inside each of us. They served as crucial members in the society of the self, and were also subject to time and processes physical. Mine was a forgetful old man with wobbly, boney hands. He spent his days in the dark rooms of my mind binding disparate pages together for future retellings. Sometimes the pages flew away and landed in other hands, where they could be transformed and remembered differently. Memory is both an image and an imagining.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fe0a71dd6-e606-4476-b174-ff091ee0e228_4032x3024.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Back in Oregon, the napkin flew toward rainbow-streaked streets. I followed and was brought to an unexpected connection between meditation and inspiration. On a basic level, we navigate the world with a set of feedback-enforced models that shape our future thinking, feeling, and behaving. That is, we operate on mental heuristics that determine what we perceive, how we interpret it, and what we do in response. Sometimes this results in behavior that may not fit the demands of the current moment; it may reflect past patterning more than our truest desires and values. What certain meditations can do, then, is free us from these patterns by enabling clarity and other ways of being. Inspiration and unexpected connections naturally arise.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I had meditated earlier in the day. I had practiced remaining uninvolved with the contents of perception in the space of “open awareness”, where things could be just as they are. Here they can also potentiate as new interpretations and responses. The napkin could have just been a usual napkin: a cheap product intended for particular uses; trash once touched and used; an object loaded with prior meanings. Instead it transformed into something else entirely. It morphed into a vessel that transported me to pages of memories that were loose in my mind but not entirely lost. All of this is possible should one be open enough to receive and dwell in possibility.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I thought back to the NYC stranger and wondered what she was up to, what kind of life she was living, whether she had transitioned into the design career she longed for. Her name eventually came to mind, and I found her on social media. As I sifted through her posts and images, a smile grew inside of me and made its way to my lips. She’d gotten married and was working as a graphic designer.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>30</title>
      <link>https://philintheblank.me/posts/23-08-10-thirty/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Aug 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://philintheblank.me/posts/23-08-10-thirty/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F9ad64a41-cdbb-44b5-aabe-60ddfb78ab12_4032x3024.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Hey! It’s my birthday today.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I had planned to write a longer piece on aging, wisdom, and some other things I’ve learned along the way to 30, but honestly I don’t really want to right now. What I want to do instead is train for my half-marathon, chat with my friends (both old and new, online and off), and read good books. I want to learn new things, write songs and poems, and practice the guitar seriously again. I want to simply participate in the world and see what happens when the page isn’t my focal point anymore.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Much of my interest in writing has been about becoming the kind of person who can write well. Put another way there’s less love in the process of it than I would like to admit, at least relative to other pursuits at the moment. Maybe I’m just trying to excuse myself from the effort required to produce the kind of works I admire and enjoy reading—I’ve looked up to writers for so long. But I’m also tired of operating from a place of needing to prove something, namely that I am interesting and worthy of good company only if I can write well. This was the crux of my personal operating system for the last few years. I’m growing up though and want instead to act solely out of wonder and curiosity. Where this has taken me as of late is to music, to conversation, to novels, to dancing, to people, even to coding and statistics again.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;So off I go into other lands, for now. I’ll end on a letter I received today from a three-year younger version of myself. (P.S. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.futureme.org/&#34;&gt;Future Me&lt;/a&gt; is awesome!):&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Dear Future Me,&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;If you’re reading this right now, happy birthday. You’re fucking 30. Three zero. At the forefront of a new decade in life. Yours. Pretty exciting right?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;First, I hope that the whole coronavirus situation has been dealt with. Although it gave younger you (me) a lot more room to explore various creative pursuits in your free time (guitar, slacklining, rollerblading, etc), it has also been incredibly restrictive in the sense of knowing how the future will unfold. I am leaning into a sharp existential edge at the moment, questioning daily everything I had thought I ever wanted. I still want to travel wide and far for extended periods of time, live in foreign countries, have deep experiences, and so on, but it’s hard to imagine how I will do all of that when the world remains mired in so much uncertainty. These past few weeks in particular have been full of doubts about whether or not I’m on the right path being in the Complex Systems and Data Science program. I’ve been thinking a lot about clinical psychology again, but it doesn’t feel quite like what I want. It feels like I want to run.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Whatever you chosen, I hope the decision was made by answering a call to something interesting and exciting rather than a reaction based in fear. Maybe you’re biking across the country like you once said you would. Imagining it now excites the hell out of me. I hope you’re following your gut. Continue creating and sharing with others a life worth living, one you’ll someday write about and regale your children with. I know for certain that the existential questions will never leave you, but hopefully you’re better equipped to hold them in your mind than I currently am. Hopefully by then you’ll also have a greater sense of inner peace and self-compassion. I like to imagine that you’re rocking a new tattoo too.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;If you’re dating anyone, show the lovely lady this letter, kiss her senselessly, and remember what drew you to her: hopefully her positive energy, her infectious laugh, her love of books, her independent and intelligent spirit, the way you can talk about anything with her while trying really hard not to lose yourself in her mesmerizing eyes. Someone kind and understanding, who pushes me to be the best version of myself. Someone you can just BE with. Remember too that great relationships are made in how you hold the tension between knowing and not knowing, distance and closeness, vulnerability and understanding. (And take any advice Younger You is giving with a grain of salt because he’s incredibly naive).&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Wherever you’re at, I hope you’re happy and proud of what you are doing. It’s tough now, but things tend to have a way of working out for you, whether by sheer luck, grit, or your ability to find meaning in any situation. Tell the people in your life you love them. Especially S for being the voice of reason and unconditional acceptance, the rock who has been with you through every fumble of your adult life, the person who has set the bar high for what it means to be a true friend. Give yourself a hug. Happy birthday.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&#xA;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Running</title>
      <link>https://philintheblank.me/poems/23-08-05-running/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Aug 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://philintheblank.me/poems/23-08-05-running/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;They asked for his time,&#xA;not how he got here.&#xA;Let me wonder then:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Did he stumble?&#xA;Did his body crumble&#xA;at all like&#xA;a soggy crepe&#xA;held up by sticks&#xA;on his way&#xA;to some&#xA;pre-determined&#xA;somewhere?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Or did he bumble&#xA;like a bee, all grace&#xA;&amp;amp; no trace of&#xA;a single step,&#xA;every toe kissing&#xA;the asphalt&#xA;as if it were&#xA;dirt?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The numbers reveal&#xA;one thing while hiding&#xA;everything else.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dog Days Are Over</title>
      <link>https://philintheblank.me/posts/23-07-31-dog-days/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 31 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://philintheblank.me/posts/23-07-31-dog-days/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fca42c8f1-0364-4496-af61-3c7f8b4c52d8_3022x2741.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Every day out the door is a new adventure for you. Each step you take holds within it a possibility, an everything all at once, waiting to burst like the teeth of zippers on jeans too intimate with skin. You bring us to squirrels with peach seeds in their mouths; to robins hopping along the grass on their reptilian feet; to stray humans, walking or jogging, in and out of our line of sight. Whatever it is, at any time of day, the movements of the moment go fully noticed. We walk our well-worn routes, zipping and trotting and bumbling along in search of the forlorn in the familiar.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Something snaps—a twig, crumbled blades of grass, self-control. You bolt like lightning after the culprit: an empty-handed squirrel. I hold on and think of how envious monks must be of your dogged focus. Nothing escapes the laser of your nose, that porous interface with which you give shape to your world. You’re a subject of impulse, but I want to believe there is intention behind your eyes too. You bring me here after all. While I sift in and out of total awareness around the clock, you swim in the constant stream of the present.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Another dog has your gaze, a pup as appealing as a bone. The barking begins, self-consciousness churns. She’s not mine! I’m just her sitter! I pull you aside to quiet you down, but your eyes are fixed. There’s tension on the leash. You want to smell him, assess if he’s a threat, feel out his vibe. Every muscle is contracted, primed to lunge. It’s control and restraint versus freedom and desire. We move into the graveyard that prohibits dogs. The tracks here are quieter.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Back in the apartment you tease me with your chew toy, pretend to yield it only to yank it away at the last second. I grab it after chasing you for awhile and pull you into a hold. Both of us are feral when we wrestle, though your bites are nips, a pearly kind of playfulness. It astounds me, your ability to discern rough-housing from danger. You could bite my face off if you wanted, and the urge in me to strike back is strong, enlivening, animalistic. Your teeth hit me like a shot of adrenaline, filling me with the energy to crush you like a candy cane—but I grit my own and hug you instead. In the minutes it takes me to make a coffee, you’re already out cold by the foot of my work desk.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I look at you in your sleep and remember: once, you pooped three times in a single walk. Only two of the loads ended up in trash bins—I didn’t have enough poop bags on me. Your third proceeded to live rent-free on the corner of some poor soul’s lawn. This is bad etiquette, I know. But we marched on. Guilt can’t morph into shame without any witnesses. You were holier than me: you kept turning your head back. I lean down to kiss the top of your head, and you kiss me back on the ear. Love is dealing with your shit.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Birdsong</title>
      <link>https://philintheblank.me/posts/23-07-13-birdsong/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://philintheblank.me/posts/23-07-13-birdsong/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fdc281577-e6e9-450a-a7e0-8abdb83c0702_720x540.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;Elizabeth Anderegg | Macaulay Library&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Every morning, I wake to a chorus of birdsong. Sometimes it is accompanied by rain, but mostly there is the sputtering of other early birds. They’re hairy bipeds without the ability to fly, though they do have the ingenuity for it. Today their cars and yet-oiled minds are starting and revving, preparing to drive off to only God knows where in the green mountain state. None of the shops here are open earlier than seven am, so I picture them driving to the head of a hiking trail, Camel’s Hump maybe. It’s possible too that they may be the poor souls who have to prepare the coffee and pastries I will leisure over later while lingering on last night’s fuzzy dreams and their associated meanings.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;There is only the rain and birdsong this morning. I reach for my phone, but an unfamiliar trill seizes my mind: “Da-da-da da-da-da da… da-da-da da-da-da da.” Seven quick notes in three parts per breath ringing in a medium-to-high register, likely from an efficient, small-breasted body. I run through my embarrassingly short and unspecific list of identifiers: Blue Jay, Northern Cardinal, House Sparrow, Robin? The bird app—no not Twitter—&lt;a href=&#34;https://merlin.allaboutbirds.org/&#34;&gt;Merlin&lt;/a&gt; confirms that she’s something else. She’s a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.allaboutbirds.org/guide/Carolina_Wren/sounds&#34;&gt;Carolina Wren&lt;/a&gt;, meaning that she is actually a He since the wren can sing. He is singing, I know, because there is a structure and cadence to it. There is also my attraction to his voice, not merely a noticing or narrowing of attention. How something so little can seize the entirety of my awareness remains a delightful mystery. I get up and go to find him.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Why do birds sing? When I sing, I expend energy that might be better spent elsewhere, especially because I am not attracting potential mates with my voice any time soon. (Though it may ward off possible aggressors.) Improvement is a possibility, though practice and effort is required. The same is true for songbirds. They must learn how to sing just like us. This begins in a critical learning period, where, as nestlings, they are highly attuned to the sounds and songs of their environment, especially those of their parents. They are listening closely as the inner pathways of their language develop. Mechanistically, this is enabled by the syrinx, the feathered equivalent of our vocal box. Once ejected from the nest, they practice replicating the songs and calls of their early days on their own.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;They have been awake for awhile now. They are always the first to rise and meet the sun with calls and melodies that color and punctuate the morning air. Scientists don’t know why they tend to sing more at dawn than any other time of day, but I like to believe that they’re grateful for the gift of another sunrise. We should be more like them. It’s possible, certainly, just like it’s possible to become a better singer. Everyone is still asleep though. Even the dogs have yet to yield a yawn, though occasionally I find the eyes of lazed cats through the dark veil of a cross-hatched windowpane.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Carolina Wren has a repertoire of song and call variations that betray his small, brown, teapot-shaped frame. They can be found up and down the eastern coast of the US, singing at nearly all hours of the day, sometimes in duets, defying scientific generalization. I can’t find the one that I’ve set out to find—unsurprising, since they are notoriously difficult to spot visually—but it seems that he has found me. In the woods and the wilds, this is always the case. There is so much here that we cannot see and perceive. And yet it is all aware of us. Every breath and footstep we take reverberates across this vast web of unknowns. We are made part and parcel in its presence, and thus more whole. Only in stillness does the world reveal itself to us.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I am most content while in rhythm and motion, but the wooded soothsayers have arrested me in lullaby. A mosquito finds my ear; I brush it off and wait. I cannot sit around and read all day, like I usually do. I cannot consider and struggle with the calculus of abstractions at all hours of the clock. I must be outside and walk, too. In the woods, by bodies of water, drenched in sunlight, draped by darkness, my thoughts become something else, less domineering in the frame of existence, no longer my own. The sun is up and the wren continues to elude my gaze, but I am still, waiting.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;hr&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.allaboutbirds.org/guide/Carolina_Wren/sounds&#34;&gt;All About Birds&lt;/a&gt; is an awesome resource for learning about (and listening to!) numerous species of birds. Check it out!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Repetition in Mary Oliver&#39;s &#34;Wild Geese&#34;</title>
      <link>https://philintheblank.me/posts/23-07-09-geese/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://philintheblank.me/posts/23-07-09-geese/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%253A%252F%252Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%252Fpublic%252Fimages%252F5dd33533-4739-4cb0-b9a7-f9596d48a527_2523x4028.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Wild Geese&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;You do not have to be good.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;You do not have to walk on your knees&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;for a hundred miles through the desert repenting.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;You only have to let the soft animal of your body&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;love what it loves.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Tell me about despair, yours, and I will tell you mine.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile the world goes on.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile the sun and the clear pebbles of the rain&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;are moving across the landscapes,&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;over the prairies and the deep trees,&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;the mountains and the rivers.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile the wild geese, high in the clean blue air,&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;are heading home again.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Whoever you are, no matter how lonely,&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;the world offers itself to your imagination,&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;calls to you like the wild geese, harsh and exciting&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;over and over announcing your place&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;in the family of things.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;hr&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Wild Geese&amp;rdquo; was the first poem I ever memorized. It&amp;rsquo;s cliché, I know, and so was the setting: I was feeling lost and lonely while walking the Camino de Santiago, days after my Camino soulmate had finished their pilgrimage. This took place over five years ago, when I was desperately trying to &amp;ldquo;figure my shit out.&amp;rdquo; I lacked any sense of direction and wanted more than anything to feel at home in the world.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This made me feel bad about myself because I wasn&amp;rsquo;t present half the time I was walking. I was wrapped up in finding the answer, as if it were sitting in the back of a statistics textbook. (Spoiler alert: I checked in graduate school&amp;mdash;it&amp;rsquo;s not there!) When the weight of the world felt too heavy to carry, I recited &amp;ldquo;Wild Geese&amp;rdquo; to myself.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I didn&amp;rsquo;t read much poetry growing up. I was more partial to drawing, fiction, Captain Underpants, and video games. So if there was any sort of deeper meaning hidden in the poem, it surely flew in one ear and out the other. The lines served simply as buoys against the uncertainty of the future. Would I have enough money to finish the trip? What was I going to do when it was all over? They grounded me when what I needed most was the smell of Spanish soil.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m revisiting it now with a sharper eye as a way to train my poetic sensibilities, and to gain a deeper appreciation of poetry in general. It seems more critical these days that we cultivate a sense of magic/poetics/the divine given the domineering effects of our omniscient, omnipotent &lt;a href=&#34;https://erikhoel.substack.com/p/exit-the-supersensorium&#34;&gt;supersensoriums&lt;/a&gt;. We need to carve out refuges where we can devote our attention to all that touches our souls, to what can &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/20943.How_to_Read_and_Why&#34;&gt;startle us out of our sleep-of-death into a more capacious sense of life.&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Poems are well-equipped for the task. They require that the television&amp;mdash;and all our supersensoriums&amp;mdash;be turned off. They demand close, careful, repeated readings. They ask, with all the affordances of paper and time, for our imagination and perseverance. In return, we are put in the presence of enriching company, both dead and alive. Your pockets may not be fuller afterwards, but your hearts may be. This alone is worth more than anything.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;hr&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Okay. Let&amp;rsquo;s take a closer look at Mary Oliver&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;Wild Geese.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Wild Geese&amp;rdquo; is centered around a single arc. The heart of it reassures us that it is always possible to find a sense of belonging in the natural world. What more is it than that? Well, part of what makes a poem a poem is the delivery, how it&amp;rsquo;s composed. Here it feels simple and straight-forward, which is what people tend to love about Oliver&amp;rsquo;s poems. For some this is a point of &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.newyorker.com/magazine/2017/11/27/what-mary-olivers-critics-dont-understand&#34;&gt;criticism&lt;/a&gt;, but simplicity itself is not a vice, nor is complexity a virtue. What matters is how these elements are woven together to give us the poem&amp;rsquo;s intended effect.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Many of Mary Oliver&amp;rsquo;s poems are prayer-like, almost biblical in nature. This is certainly true of her works in the collection Devotions. There&amp;rsquo;s a reverence to them, an expansiveness that I feel after reading her verse when my mind is quiet and open. We can attribute this, in part, to the way she employs repetition. Repetition can be used to reinforce a point or message or felt sense. This can take form in the words themselves, or the images, themes, and feelings evoked throughout a poem. They can damn us, as when used for the ends of shaming, or they can serve as the mantras that heal us over time.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m reminded of the ten commandments from the Bible at the beginning of &amp;ldquo;Wild Geese&amp;rdquo;: &lt;em&gt;Thou shalt not kill&amp;hellip; Thou shalt not steal&amp;hellip; Thou shalt not use the word Thou Ten Thousand times in a row&amp;hellip;&lt;/em&gt; This seems intentional when considering the central image in the first chunk of verse (The set of Yous). We have a &lt;strong&gt;repenting&lt;/strong&gt; individual, one who is walking through a &lt;strong&gt;desert&lt;/strong&gt; on their &lt;strong&gt;knees&lt;/strong&gt; in search of redemption. The word choice and repeating Yous draws on our society&amp;rsquo;s religious roots, suggesting that our wanderer can only be saved by something bigger than themselves. And yet, the section ends with:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;You only have to let the soft animal of your body&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;love what it loves.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Rather than turn outward toward a religious kind of revival, Oliver appeals to our animal selves, to our basic, pre-religious nature. &lt;em&gt;You do not have to &lt;strong&gt;be good&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; she invokes, because goodness is rooted in human morality. We can find salvation elsewhere she suggests, in something more fundamental.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We now arrive to the &lt;em&gt;meanwhiles&lt;/em&gt;. These lines are structured similarly to the &lt;em&gt;yous&lt;/em&gt;, where the first line depicts an abstraction (&lt;em&gt;good&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;world&lt;/em&gt;), the second line an image of nature (a desert, a dynamic landscape), the last an animal (the soft animal of your body, wild geese). Note, too, that the content within the &lt;em&gt;meanwhiles&lt;/em&gt; is growing more vivid relative to their parallel yous, which has the effect of adding richness and momentum to the poem. We are moving from &lt;em&gt;good&lt;/em&gt; to &lt;em&gt;the world&lt;/em&gt;, from &lt;em&gt;the soft animal of your body&lt;/em&gt; to &lt;em&gt;wild geese&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The expectation as a reader, now, is that some sort of resolution must be reached. We have allowed the soft animal of our bodies to love what they love; we have shared our despair with one another; we have witnessed the evolving landscape, the wild geese flying in the clean blue air. Where is the poem taking us?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In the end, Oliver breaks away from her structured repetitions, leaving us with a long verse spilling over several lines. The poem has been building up to this point, repeating itself and its images until at last it resolves into a quiet crescendo. The world is offering itself to you, the wild geese are calling to you, all neatly constrained by the strength of the commas.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;And then no longer. The commas are are overrun, and we&amp;rsquo;re left with a final repetition&amp;mdash; &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;over and over&lt;/strong&gt; announcing your place in the family of things&lt;/em&gt; &amp;mdash;and two enjambments&amp;mdash; &lt;em&gt;harsh and exciting / over and over announcing your place / in the family of things&lt;/em&gt; &amp;mdash; as if, finally, we have arrived, as if the geese and our imaginations are dancing with each other.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;hr&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“Wild Geese” begins and ends the way a river does, from the smallness of you at the mouth of the poem, to the expansive refuge that is available when we widen the aperture of our imaginations. The Yous build us up toward the release of despair. The meanwhiles set the stage and lead us to the image of wild geese heading home, again, implicating that this is always on offer for us. And then the poem ends with a final statement, one that condenses the structure and repetitions that have been strewn throughout, reposing in a sense of arrival:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Whoever &lt;strong&gt;you&lt;/strong&gt; are, no matter how lonely,&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;the world&lt;/strong&gt; offers itself to your imagination,&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;calls to you like &lt;strong&gt;the wild geese&lt;/strong&gt;, harsh and exciting&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;over and over announcing your place&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;in the family of things.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Why go through the mess of reading a poem like this? A more direct person might have said to you “if you’re feeling lost and down about yourself, go into nature.” Partly because life often feels like going through the mess of a poem. We receive banal platitudes and thoughtless advice all the time. But we change only when we ourselves embark on &lt;a href=&#34;http://thepracticelondon.org/poetry/poems-of-transformation-the-journey-by-mary-oliver/&#34;&gt;the journey&lt;/a&gt;. Sometimes this actually involves working through the nuances of a poem. In the process, you may discover something beautiful. You may find another layer of existence that enriches the way you witness and navigate your life. You may arrive at an answer, or, more than likely, further questions that have the power to guide you.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Solstice &amp; seagulls</title>
      <link>https://philintheblank.me/posts/23-06-26-solstice/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Jun 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://philintheblank.me/posts/23-06-26-solstice/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd3f57f0a-9707-44db-82b4-40bc15b7db5a_4028x2610.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We’re grouped on the grass by the lake, somewhere on the periphery of jazz fest, planning a solstice party. Musicians unknown to us enchant and move the crowd, but we are neither enchanted nor moved, mostly because we are plebeians who throw around artless smiles (ty Chekhov for this phrase) like Oprah on The Oprah Winfrey Show. Still, we try to move anyways. We bob and sway and kick and swing and move but fail to dance with swag. Now our artless smiles are accompanied by artless moves. We’re vibing though, which is what counts I’m told.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I like this, kind of. We like this. We are happy enough and buzzing because we are surrounded by boats we cannot afford and music we don’t normally listen to and sunsets we get to catch every day and each other. A wolf spider perks up from his den in the crack of a lamppost and joins us. We welcome him and name him something important I know I won’t remember the next day. Our problems are held by the company and music, transformed even, made lighter for tomorrow.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;And then the Stump game is proposed. E promises the stump will be easy to find and transport to the party. She knows a guy she says. This amuses us and settles the discussion. We’re amused at how easily amused we are. Our smiles are no more nuanced by the end of the night, but they continue to beam as we dream.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;hr&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;It’s actually there, one week later, in the backseat of her scrappy Nissan, a full tree stump, heavy, thick, and aged, perfect for our purposes. I’m reminded of hands and the way veins contort like bark. The only thing E says about it is that she forgot to put a blanket under it before lugging it into her car. This strikes me as something E would say but not do. She isn’t afraid of a little dirt, is she? It’s so thoughtful of her to think of it.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We drive to the party with no further questions. We talk about the weather, which ends in the philosophical musings of amateurs and the lightness of unencumbered laughter. I’ve got my guitar, a hammer, some nails. When we arrive I roll the stump out as casually as possible toward the others. They are situated around a bonfire, waiting for our arrival to begin.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Hammers weren’t meant to be thrown in the air, but neither were humans. This is how G ends up with a bleeding thumb. A plate follows a similar fate, shattering into more fractions than God can count. We continue at it for awhile, flipping the $10 hammer into the sky like jugglers. Some of us catch it more often than others; an even smaller handful manages to sink a nail into the wood. A crushes us in the first round, his first ever, leaving our mouths agape and my mind full of backstories to explain his performance. Something’s not computing because he is a city boy. But before I can ask he’s gone, claiming that he is a reasonable man with work to attend in the morning. No one mentions that we do, too.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The moon takes its place in the cloudless night, as E steers our attention to Venus hovering right below. We stay and play until we can no longer endure the mosquitoes that have proven they are bolder and larger than life. I’m prepared to sing a song I wrote, but fear chokes me up at the last minute.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;hr&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In the morning there’s a seagull eating a dead mackerel beside one of the graveyards I frequently walk by. It’s early and he’s alone with me, stabbing his beak into the gill of the lifeless fish with the kind of precision only dreamed of by darts players in speakeasys and statisticians on Twitter. I wonder if he’ll bury it when he’s done, given the nearby graveyard. Surrounding him are the remains of dropped groceries: a half-open can of tomatoes, broken glass, the crispy skin of exposed garlic cloves.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The seagull stutters away from the mackerel when I step closer for a better look. He doesn’t want me to catch him feasting on what cannot defend itself. It’s a gull eat gull world I whisper behind crusty eyes. This one has more pride than the rest, though I notice that, when I turn back toward him and his prize, he has his back toward me.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;He really doesn’t want to be caught eating this fish. He’s not some schmuck of a seagull who vultures around humans all day in the hopes that fate will be kind to him. He’s better than this—he’s a pioneer, a self-made seagull who knows how to find his own food, not a freewheeling freeloader with wings. But we’re connected, too. When I move, he moves. When I turn, he turns. We do our dance for awhile, only to find the back of our respective heads when we try to observe the other.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;There are others in the distance. I begin to picture them as capitalistic graverobbers with top hats and fancy suits that are abandoned when it’s time to eat. And what they eat, in my mind, are deceased humans. To them we’re wasteful; it’s a simple resource allocation problem, and they’re willing to solve it efficiently. Maybe this is why, Ms. Emily Dickinson, they never - in extremity - &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.poetryfoundation.org/poems/42889/hope-is-the-thing-with-feathers-314&#34;&gt;asked a crumb&lt;/a&gt; of you. Maybe they never needed to.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;When I scurry away far enough, I witness him in the act. His beak connects, finds a vein, cranes and twists, until sinew surrenders to strength.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;hr&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Another summer solstice, another beginning and ending all at once.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I’m trying with all my might to tease apart beginnings from endings because it’s better for the story of my life. But who and what we are is an ongoing process, a tangled knot of beginnings and an endings threaded in a swirl of cosmic hairballs. I’ve had my share of endings recently and want to focus only on this beginning, on one thread. But I know that this wishful thinking, which may never end for as long as I live. The beginnings are the endings are the beginnings.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The heat is getting to me. It’s worsening my sleep and blurring the line between one day and the next. It might be the smoke, too, from my Canadians up north. The U.S. army once tried (maybe they’re still trying) to reduce the need for sleep in their soldiers. This makes me sad because these super soldiers would no longer be human. Without sleep we cannot dream, and to dream is to be human.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;And yet, we dream more by dreaming less. We forget what we know in our lack of sleep and memory and rely instead on imagination to fill in the gaps. Summer, then, makes us more human by helping us forget who we were, allowing us to shape who we are and who we want to be. The beginnings are the endings are the beginnings.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I sometimes dream that I’ll be rich enough to fund the dreams and projects of my friends. One friend wants to build a house in Maine where she and her hens can live. She also wishes for an extra 80 years to live in it, which means that if I am to succeed, I will need the folks working on human longevity to accelerate their work for humans and hens alike.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I dream, too, of finding my traveling companions for the longer walk of life. I think this will include a pup, and surely a wifey and children at some point. It also includes friends and people who are dedicated to lifelong explorations. Ideally they are experts in embodied phenomenology and creative goofology, people who can point to a tree or word or song or yam and make me fall in love with it. They are lovers and rebels and artsy intellectuals, people who can challenge me for the sake of deepening my love for the world. In return I can give my hands and words and energy. I can make something beautiful from the messiness of beginnings and endings.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Being held by the world</title>
      <link>https://philintheblank.me/posts/23-06-16-held/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Jun 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://philintheblank.me/posts/23-06-16-held/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I’m going through a break-up. We’d gotten back together months ago and tried to make things work again, but most of the time it was more painful than not. I tried to muscle through the pain, but relationships are not meant to be muscled through. There was always something that prevented me from opening up and being my full self, which inevitably led to distance and disappointment. This made me realize, among other things, that I believed I was never supposed to let others down, especially my loved ones. As a result I let myself down, and her as well. We talked through our issues and wishes and reached a mutual understanding that this was the most loving thing we could do for each other.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;It feels different this time, thankfully. There’s a greater sense of acceptance, a quiet spaciousness and strength that is allowing me to grieve properly. I get sad when I see old photos and our memorabilia (I’m sad writing this!). But I also feel steady and content with the decision. We certainly had our wonderful moments: moments of happiness and grace, of care and forgiveness, of silliness and play. We also put the other’s patience to practice (ha) and learned how to better navigate difficult conversations. Before me she didn’t believe that love was worth fighting for, nor did she think she could feel it so deeply. Now she does. And in more than words and daydreams, I learned what love is.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;hr&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The next day I woke up early and couldn’t fall back asleep. I went outside and decided to walk up the bike path by the lake for a few hours. Memories and flashbacks flickered like torches in the dark night of consciousness. Wild Geese later came to mind as I got closer to my destination. I recited the poem a few times like a mantra until I reached the cove. The water was calm, the skies overcast. Beside me were the remains of a recent fire. I reached into the pit for scraps of charcoal and began writing my favorite lines into the rock. A peaceful, trance-like state overcame me. My fingers darkened with each line, and then it was done. I turned toward the dolostone surrounding me and thought of my friend who fell somewhere nearby years ago. It was a 70ft fall, one that she survived.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Later I’m approached by two women. They’re friendly and ask if they can look at what I’d written. One of them tells me she’s a native of the land, a woman of the Abenaki. We talk briefly before our eyes settle on the horizon, where the Adirondacks stand grand and timeless. She then asks if she can sing a song for me in the language of her people. Her voice is gentle and reassuring like the wind, firm and strong too like the thrust fault that birthed this place. The song carries itself over three lines I don’t understand but feel held by. In the quiet warmth that follows her last note she hugs me tightly and wishes me well. I run into them again on the way out, and the Abenaki woman hands me a hawk feather and says: I think he dropped it for you.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;hr&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;On the walk home, I think to myself (and am reminded by a dear friend) that these sorts of things happen to me with a strange frequency. Whoever, whatever is watching over me, all I can say is, I feel held. I see the signs, the doors and invitations, and I know I have to keep walking this way.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ff2c1b9bf-ad0e-4809-9d81-1cf0d87e38ff_3024x4032.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Holding my friend&#39;s baby</title>
      <link>https://philintheblank.me/posts/23-05-22-baby/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://philintheblank.me/posts/23-05-22-baby/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F0c46550f-80c2-40cc-8fd4-1617de33e8ec_3024x4032.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;It’s graduation day, a day that seems more important to everyone else but me, not because I don’t find it significant, but because I get to see O for the first time. He’s sleeping when I arrive at N’s parent’s house, so I make my rounds around the room and indulge myself in some food. There’s an assortment of delicious buns from a local bakery, chips and dip of average quality from Trader Joes, homemade mocktails on tap, and I haven’t eaten yet. The house pup greets me like I’m family despite the contrast of my southeast Asian glow to that of the Vermonters I love.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The last time I was here was right before I officiated N &amp;amp; M’s wedding. I met N five years ago when I moved from California to Vermont for a job in a developmental neuroscience lab. We shared an office where we often goofed off and talked about science, books, astrology, and other kinds of heady deliciousness for hours. It was a sad day when she moved a couple of feet down the hall—it makes a ginormous difference in the ease of conversation!—and even sadder still when she got accepted to med school. I was happy for her too of course, and thankfully she’d be attending the local university with M! But I knew that med school had the tendency to eat people and their friendships alive.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;A year or two later, I ran into N at the grocery store. She caught me in one of the darkest moods I’d ever been. We chatted over dinner, and I learned that she was getting married. She was also pregnant and wanted me to officiate her wedding. This put me in one of the best moods I’d ever been. We had made the occasional effort to catch up in town while she was trudging through her first few years of med school, but it wasn’t the same as sharing an office together. So I was ecstatic that she’d chosen me to do the honors.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;And what an honor it was. Everyone was situated in a beautiful, open field on a blisteringly hot day. A light breeze was present. Umbrellas were docked throughout the ceremony area. I was nervous, but everything went smoothly. I led her family and friends through a short meditation involving oranges and chocolate, quoted David Whyte’s &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=5scnhCFuWiI&#34;&gt;Friendship&lt;/a&gt;, and half-successfully kept my tears in check. N &amp;amp; M sang a cappella together in college. This was central to the formation of their then budding relationship. The night ended on the high note of their individual and duo performances. O was there, steadily growing in the womb, listening to the kind of music that can only be produced by love.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;When it came time to choose between N’s graduation party and my own graduation ceremony, it was a no-brainer. There too was always a part of me that felt distant from my program and the work I was doing, which I’m still unpacking a bit. Regardless, I’d choose celebrating and seeing my friends over anything any day.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I’d choose over and over again to bounce O on my leg as he chews and slobbers over a cardboard tag attached to the new plushie his grandmother has just given him. He’s looking at me with innocent eyes, with a gaze free from expectation that puts me ease, scanning the ridges of my face and my acne scars and my darkened skin and my crooked smile like little curiosities, not anomalies that need correction. He has no notion of what it means to size someone up, the way we adults do.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;He laughs with and at me regardless of whether or not I have a masters or medical degree, even if I am no comedian. He smiles because I have done something funny, and for no reason at all. His wispy tuft of hair reminds me of clouds and cotton candy, his two bottom teeth of pebbles on a gummy coastline. These baby things are kind of amazing, I tell myself.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I think of what science can tell us about babies, about the variability in the development of certain milestones like the ability to crawl, walk, and talk. How fast these things happen—so fast that they seem like discrete events. One moment they’re here, the next they’re twenty-nine years old pondering the nature of things, hopelessly aware of how transient life is. My attention is fixed on him like a laser, as if I can engrave the moment into marble. He looks back at me, and reminds me to soften.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Graduation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;div class = &#34;poem&#34;&gt;&#xA;* We look to our future days&#xA;* with eager eyes to behold—&#xA;* But don&#39;t run so quickly!&#xA;* Too soon you&#39;ll be old.&#xA;* The worlds that need your saving&#xA;* are here with us now.&#xA;* Our minds are the soil,&#xA;* the heart is our plow.&#xA;* Sow the seeds and wait,&#xA;* let the stories be told.&#xA;* Hold your heart steady&#xA;* as our future days unfold.&#xA;&lt;/div&gt;&#xA;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Great Blue Heron</title>
      <link>https://philintheblank.me/posts/23-05-16-heron/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://philintheblank.me/posts/23-05-16-heron/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F8caf25af-48fc-4c61-84a2-224fc140b070_4032x3024.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;It’s lap one and already I’m questioning myself. My knees are talking to me like the old wooden floorboards of a house that has endured a million greasy footsteps while the cool Spring air has learned how to burn like hot coals in my lungs. The sky is so blue and cloudless so why don’t I just stop and walk and enjoy the vastness that is this life my life and oh my god my bed how I miss it so! I want to emerge like a butterfly from his cocoon and be changed, more powerful, but I do not want to change.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The sun is staring me down on lap two. Go find someone or something prettier to look at I yell at him. He laughs in response, knowing that he will always be a constant companion. Dust has gathered on the new shoes I bought just for this occasion, and I curse at the ground for being too damn dusty. What are you running from? Maybe I’m running toward something. What is all this work for? For me, for the work itself. Why don’t you have any answers? Because I’m still searching for them. I want to be a butterfly and I don’t know how to be a butterfly.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Suddenly she’s there on lap three. I do a double take to make sure she’s real. What are you doing here? You don’t belong here. Where do I belong? My legs continue to propel me forward but my body remains twisted toward the heron. She’s standing as still as a statue, scanning the field, searching for her prey. I think of butterflies and Mary Oliver’s Wild Geese. You do not have to be good. / You do not have to walk on your knees for a hundred miles through the desert repenting. So much is moving in her lack of movement. You only have to let the soft animal of your body / love what it loves. I round the bend.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Lap four comes around and I’m feeling thankful for endorphins and the kind of ingenuity that led to their discovery and hence my own. How little I remember of neuroscience, but she’s still there, my winged muse. Tell me about despair, yours, and I will tell you mine. I recount the year’s achings and yearnings, my desire for the kind of certainty I sought through Ellie and her swaying crosshair in The Last of Us. I think of Abby, that bitch, and Joel. Love makes a fool of us, and vengeance too.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I end my run and take a final look at the heron. She is a walking invitation for the imagination. She is a suburb brought to life. She flies away, seconds later. Whoever you are, no matter how lonely, / the world offers itself to your imagination. What do you think Mary Oliver? Change doesn’t happen in the blink of an eye, but sometimes everything does change all at once. I dust off my shoes and run another lap.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ok boomer</title>
      <link>https://philintheblank.me/posts/23-05-03-boomer/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://philintheblank.me/posts/23-05-03-boomer/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F14d63f2c-1376-4f16-bd51-b6041dc28f5a_4032x3024.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I have this insecurity about not remembering things. When I talk with people I want to perfectly recall the details of their lives—who did what, where, how they felt about such and such—otherwise it makes me feel like a bad person, like I didn’t try hard enough or care enough to give my full attention. Sometimes this is true, as much as I hate to admit. To care is to put yourself out there, meaning that you’ve got to open up your heart, something I struggle with at times. Old wounds. Other times I simply forget things. Facts and abstractions tend to be more salient than what I ate for lunch because they latch onto the mental models I’ve constructed over the years. Though I still like to believe that I will remember the way you made me feel ten summers ago.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;hr&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The clerk rings up my book in a slow, unenthused series of motions. His shirt looks like something out of a Gen-Z fashion blog, cheap but chic and trendy. I ask him about it and it takes him awhile to register the question, as if he’d never been asked before. Too much time in cyberspace? Waiting for his response, I start to feel like the annoyingly energetic customer who happens to be in the best of Saturday moods while the underpaid employee is still waiting for the caffeine to clock in. His soul is still waiting for him at the door. “It’s just a meme. Haven’t you seen it?”&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I recall my childhood and the patchy scar dotting my lower back, an unavoidable consequence of boyish arrogance, a mini electric pocket bike, and speed bumps. There too are the times I snuck into the nursery behind my neighborhood with my friends to fight each other with borrowed bamboo sticks on giant dirt mounds. More scars than stars ever counted, but we were all the happier for them.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Back in the car I think to myself that kids probably don’t do this anymore. It’s shunned even, all in the name of safety and extracurriculars. And why fiddle with dirt and bamboo sticks when there are smart devices, escapes from suburbia only a swipe away? A fraction of them might actually be doing cool things in the digital ether, but I worry about their willingness and desire to remain in touch with the physical world, that place I love and know and respect, one that has nurtured us for generations. “Ok boomer” is probably the proper response to my grievances, but I know I’m not the only one sounding the sirens.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;When I start the engine Keith Johnstone’s Impro comes to mind. Haven’t you seen it? Oh god damnit. Did the kid just put me in my place?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;hr&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Me and this old guy in the coffee shop aren’t so different. He’s here alone, nursing a coffee with a newspaper he doesn’t seem intent on reading. Not the greatest eyesight, judging by the thickness of his specs. No wedding ring, no agenda for the rest of the day. What differentiates us is that he puts sugar in his coffee while I drink mine black. What does that tell you about our generation?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The shop owner is the subject of his searching gaze, as the old guy is to mine. He’s watching him serve the customers while I continue to sketch my mental caricature. I’m half-reading as to be ready to avert my eyes at the faintest hint of being detected. We like to watch but not be watched. I wonder who is watching me?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;And then there’s laughter. It’s feminine, open, whole-hearted. The owner is speaking to two women in a tongue I can’t understand, connecting with them in a way that I never could in my younger years. I’ve never been the funny one, but I do amuse myself often. I can live with amusing. A smile crosses my lips upon realizing that he didn’t try as hard with me to make me laugh. This makes me laugh, and I curse him for his indirect comedy.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lessons from RRR</title>
      <link>https://philintheblank.me/poems/04-10-23-rrr/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://philintheblank.me/poems/04-10-23-rrr/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Sometimes a rhyme is good.&#xA;Avoid all shrouds and sometimes&#xA;repetition too. Subtract words&#xA;as needed, maybe all of them.&#xA;Keep one ear close to the page&#xA;and listen&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;to the heartbeat&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;of every word, every space,&#xA;every line; see how lines&#xA;define&#xA;and break&#xA;and keep steady the pace&#xA;of a poem. And remember that&#xA;heart is at the center of it all.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Birds</title>
      <link>https://philintheblank.me/poems/04-06-23-birds/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://philintheblank.me/poems/04-06-23-birds/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;One moment I’m a philosopher, all words&#xA;and fat with truth. The next I’m a poet&#xA;moonlighting for something new to say.&#xA;I’ve tried on the certainty of equations&#xA;since they promised me the last word.&#xA;But I liked the birds instead, every word&#xA;of theirs a spell that guarantees&#xA;the truth of my existence,&#xA;that truths are truisms&#xA;only sometimes true,&#xA;that Truth itself lies&#xA;within and beyond&#xA;what can be said&#xA;and has been said&#xA;with words.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Oranges</title>
      <link>https://philintheblank.me/poems/04-04-23-oranges/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://philintheblank.me/poems/04-04-23-oranges/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;What&amp;rsquo;s real&#xA;is not&#xA;ideal.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Peel&#xA;an orange&#xA;&amp;amp; feel&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;its parts,&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;how easily&#xA;the whole&#xA;breaks&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;apart&#xA;&amp;amp; still&#xA;retains&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;its tart,&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;perfection&#xA;an orange&#xA;in every bite.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Boxelder bugs</title>
      <link>https://philintheblank.me/poems/03-11-23-boxelder/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 11 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://philintheblank.me/poems/03-11-23-boxelder/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Like life, you kept finding your way through my&#xA;walls despite how many times I squished you&#xA;nudged you onto paper mail to leave you&#xA;out in the harsh winter air, where confused&#xA;you wondered what happened to the warmth of&#xA;a home that once housed your black-red body.&#xA;You looked at me with curiosity&#xA;the other day as I was about to&#xA;sweep you away. You crawled along the top&#xA;of my couch, and when I approached you turned&#xA;your body, antennae, and zigzagged legs&#xA;at me as if you knew what was coming.&#xA;In a funny way you give my days shape&#xA;consistency in my daily motions&#xA;meaning I am not creative in how&#xA;I get rid of you from my empty flat&#xA;always with guilt and a pinch of remorse&#xA;because you are there during lonely nights&#xA;in the vents, hiding in the windowsill,&#xA;always available like morning light&#xA;to spring me from my longing, to wake me&#xA;into something just beyond the outline&#xA;of my well-known interiorities.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The meaning in the sea</title>
      <link>https://philintheblank.me/posts/23-03-07-meaning-sea/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://philintheblank.me/posts/23-03-07-meaning-sea/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://images.unsplash.com/photo-1523486230352-65ff5222cea4?crop=entropy&amp;amp;cs=tinysrgb&amp;amp;fit=max&amp;amp;fm=jpg&amp;amp;ixid=MnwzMDAzMzh8MHwxfHNlYXJjaHwxfHxvY3RvcHVzfGVufDB8fHx8MTY3ODIwNDUyOQ&amp;amp;ixlib=rb-4.0.3&amp;amp;q=80&amp;amp;w=1080&#34; alt=&#34;Masaaki Komori&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Sometimes you read something in a book that is so moving that you can’t help feeling that something in you has literally shifted. This was the effect of chapter 28 of Ray Naylor’s “&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.raynayler.net/&#34;&gt;The Mountain in the Sea&lt;/a&gt;.” The book is, in part (there is so much in here!), an exploration of AI, octopuses (yeah, it’s octopuses, not octopi, due to the Greek origins of the word), and the ends that sentient beings will go to preserve themselves.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In times of distress, the domain of our objective functions are flattened to the sole aim of self-preservation. In the process trust is diminished, aggression and vigilance rises, others become means to an end rather than ends in themselves. Sometimes though, in the trenches of our struggles, we produce art, as if it were a necessity. There are things that must be said given the precariousness of the situation, forms of expression that must come out of us if we are not only to survive, but also retain the soul of our humanity. That may be one function of art, if we are to give it one among its many pluralities.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;An enclave of octopuses are being spied on from a camouflaged vessel. The humans have been tasked to do so in an effort to exploit what they don’t yet know about intelligence. They once believed that the octopus was a creature of solitude, one whose life span is like that of a firework, here and then gone in a brilliant blink in the grand scheme of things.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;What they find is something to the contrary. The cephalopods are also capable of communicating with one another in a form that feels both foreign and familiar to the humans. The octopus at the center is dashing off symbols into the oceanic ether. There is repetition and a cadence to the act, and then the humans realize it: the octopus is performing a poem. It’s unclear what it means. But there is something haunting and beautiful to the act as their world is being fished out of existence.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Maybe it all really does boil down to a survival function. But I’d like to think – to believe – that we live for something more, that more is living for something beyond what evolution had in mind. What survives matters. We must look beyond our genes. Beyond our bodies. Beyond utility. Perhaps we must look beyond terraria too and into the umwelt of the other worldly creatures we share a home with.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>To the child reading a book</title>
      <link>https://philintheblank.me/posts/23-03-01-child/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://philintheblank.me/posts/23-03-01-child/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fb2a12fff-623e-4d2c-be85-b500125b43ca_4032x3024.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Sitting across from me is a child with a book in hand. This sort of thing fills me with an unreasonable amount of hope for the world. She’s engrossed by the colors and a sea of static faces, as if in rebellion against the digital ocean designed to captivate us more than the ocean itself. We are drowning in the currents of the former, without any sense of beauty and movement from the latter. Fully garbed in pink, she’s delighting in showing her mother and her mother’s friend the simple happenings that populate the pages. The words are animating her young mind and soul. Her voice has filled the entirety of the café, as she bounces between being herself and the seeming fictions. The line between the two is fuzzier than we think. I don’t want to moralize, but I feel that the parents are doing something right. I see it in the ease of the child’s laugh, the joy that spreads across her lips as she plays in the ocean of her imagination. It’s thanks to her that I feel my younger self has been freed to dive aimlessly into The Mountain in the Sea, to meander in a world inspired by our own.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>baby making in progress</title>
      <link>https://philintheblank.me/posts/23-02-23-babymaking/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://philintheblank.me/posts/23-02-23-babymaking/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F0541f81a-354a-4e85-97e3-727e3a4d6f16_4032x3024.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;There is delight in the way our minds find spurious associations between things. I was looking out the window of a coffee shop at a heap of snow recently formed by an overnight storm, when suddenly my eye caught it: a small white dot on the window, and above it, a trail following a sud of soap. “Baby making in progress” was my first thought. Baby making in progress. I rolled my eyes and laughed at myself. Jesus, I thought. He would be disappointed. I was then brought back to high school health class, which reminded me of the young female teacher my friends and I oogled on the daily like helpless puppies. I don’t think we learned much in that class, but I do remember how strange it was to watch the movie on baby making. You know the one. Heavily pixelated, generic voiceover, 1990s feel to it. We, the freshmen, were deemed mature enough, supposedly, to bear witness to the miraculous, complex machinery of our collective conception. I watched, mesmerized, as animated swarms of sperm raced shoulder to shoulder in an attempt to create new life, to give themselves over for the continuation of our species. Not all of them would make it the narrator said with dramatic indifference. But, as if it were inevitable, there would be an eventual winner. There had to be, he said. That’s the promise of obsessive single-mindedness, singularity of purpose. All they ‘wanted’ to do, all they ‘lived’ for (how lovely and unavoidable our tendency to anthropomorphize) was this. And, perhaps, to stun naive, unlearned high schoolers in Southern California. I was a hopelessly lost child who knew only of video games and brotherhood. That was life, just me and the boys (though sometimes girls were involved too). But perhaps I wasn’t so different from the little swimmers that trained day in and day out within the confines of my developing body. They were my first clue that you didn’t need much to get far in life. All you needed, maybe, was intention and the willingness to swim. How delightful it is then that I am where I am, a decade and a half later, giving thanks to gravity, a watermark, a dried up soap sud, and the beautiful machinations that animate our minds.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dogs</title>
      <link>https://philintheblank.me/posts/23-02-22-dogs/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://philintheblank.me/posts/23-02-22-dogs/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://images.unsplash.com/photo-1610266784664-c60b5dbf0425?crop=entropy&amp;amp;cs=tinysrgb&amp;amp;fit=max&amp;amp;fm=jpg&amp;amp;ixid=MnwzMDAzMzh8MHwxfHNlYXJjaHwxMnx8ZG9nJTIwY29mZmVlJTIwc2hvcHxlbnwwfHx8fDE2NzcwODE1ODc&amp;amp;ixlib=rb-4.0.3&amp;amp;q=80&amp;amp;w=1080&#34; alt=&#34;Photo by Jojo Yuen (sharemyfoodd)&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In Burlington you will find a dog waiting for you around every corner. Try to hide on Hyde Street and you will eventually be barked at by Foxy the coyote-looking dog. Pop into Kru Coffee and ten of them will be waiting in line with you for your daily drip. You cannot escape them when you’re out and about in the city wilds, and that is a good thing, a very good thing.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I want to thank the humans that accompany them for being the kind of people who are willing to raise a dog, or at least for letting me, a petless, heady person, be a beneficiary of their desire and capacity to care for something other than ourselves. These folks are the public servants of joy, even if sometimes they themselves are joyless. To these individuals I am sorry for not acknowledging this, the invisible pain you sometimes carry, but your dog is way too cute for me to notice. I am a sponge for vicarious delight and want to soak up every ounce of happiness produced by your four-legged fur baby. Most of you, though, seem pretty happy.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Today one ran up to me while I was sitting at my usual table with my usual thoughts at my usual coffee shop. He stared at me for a good few seconds, and in those seconds, I felt as if he could see straight through the armor I wear. The curls covering his eyes, his scrappy disposition, all of it was enough to bring me into a weightless reverie. My worries dissipated as the moment focused in on the singularity between us. When he returned to the side of his human to receive his daily treat, I remembered what can come of surrender.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Snow</title>
      <link>https://philintheblank.me/posts/23-02-20-snow/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://philintheblank.me/posts/23-02-20-snow/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F5298a421-2ad7-4178-bcaa-e4012e6353b7_4032x3024.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Snow: so much like sand. The way it clumps, every molecule hanging together, shaped by the objects it falls on, are nothing without the whole. Its individual motes are sparkly and luminous under certain slants of sunlight. Much like us, they rely on the sun for their beauty. Snow and sand form deserted deserts in the night, free from the people and light that gave them attention. Who are we without the eye of another? Is the existence of everything instantiated by—dependent on—the existence of everything else?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Snow is formed by the lack of movement, molecules of water no longer repulsing, each attracted to the other by forces outside their control. These forces lead to its collective dance in the winter, the way it spreads over the land, trees, branches, windows, windshields. Like germs and pollen you can’t shield yourself from its consuming embrace, try as you might. With it comes the cold that pierces our layers, reminds us what it means to be alive, that life requires a certain degree of exposure, a level of vulnerability to what is outside our control. One morning it’s a winter wonderland, the next a sea of gray slush, an inconvenience for the commuters, though the birds don’t seem to mind. They continue to sing despite the weather.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The first time I saw snow I was in Times Square. It was my first time in New York City. Each drop was illuminated by buzzing signs and large billboards. Faces and feet blurred past me as I stood against time with with my body turned toward a sky dotted by snow. Snow, more sticky than the pixels we feed ourselves on. Snow, that reminder of change and seasons, that there is beauty in the extremes. Snow, the seasonal friend of rocks and graveyards who always returns. It always does.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The wooden table I always sit at</title>
      <link>https://philintheblank.me/posts/23-02-18-table/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 18 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://philintheblank.me/posts/23-02-18-table/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I am sitting at a café (so French and proper of me to include the accent over the e) that I frequently visit, a black coffee and The Book of Delights in hand. Ross Gay is a genius and delight. Every word of his makes me smile. (So wonderful that words can do such a thing!) I’d like to meet him and see the world through his eyes. His book is the next best option. Right now the sun is beaming through the window, windows I’ve gazed through countless times, as snow melts from the grooves of the rooftop above me. Who am I telling this to you ask? You, the precious table I always sit at. How many others have spilled coffee upon your surface? How many crumbs of biscuit and croissant have you yourself tasted, each colored by the mouth of tasty, chatty, quiet, solemn strangers, lovers and potential lovers, people with fates yet decided, all over your solid body, a catchall for leftovers and conversation and contemplation? Every day is new to you, even when it’s me and my crumbs again. Familiarity doesn’t scare you. All you need is attention, because despite all appearances, you are quite neglected, though it doesn’t make you too unhappy if you had to be honest, especially those split seconds when the barista is in the bathroom and the patrons are out and off to do something responsible with themselves (like work and taxes), leaving you to bask in the sun and silence, right until the door opens again and a stranger like me sits with you, perhaps to write out these exact thoughts, which are to be enjoyed over other surfaces, in beds, on screens, with coffee and a biscuit perhaps, over other wooden tables somewhere else in the world.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
